<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theosplanchnistheis, or, The yernings of Christs bowels towards his languishing friends wherein the sincereity, ardency, constancy, and super-eminent excellency of the love of Jesus Christ as it workes from him towards his friends is delineated, discussed, and fitly applyed / by S.M. ...</title>
            <author>Moore, Samuel, b. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51249</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2588</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9458</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13540529</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13540529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51249)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 796:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Theosplanchnistheis, or, The yernings of Christs bowels towards his languishing friends wherein the sincereity, ardency, constancy, and super-eminent excellency of the love of Jesus Christ as it workes from him towards his friends is delineated, discussed, and fitly applyed / by S.M. ...</title>
                  <author>Moore, Samuel, b. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 119 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matthew Symmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Sam. Moore.</note>
                  <note>Title transliterated from Greek.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [30]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100079:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100079:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> OR, The Yernings of CHRISTS bowels towards his languiſhing FRIENDS.</p>
            <p>Wherein the ſincerity, ardency, conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and ſuper-eminent excellency of the love of Jeſus Chriſt; as it workes from him towards his Friends: is delineated, diſcuſſed, and fitly applyed;</p>
            <p>BY S. M. <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>I ſaid unto thee when thou waſt in thy blood, live; Yea I ſaid unto thee when thou waſt in thy blood, live.</p>
               <p>Behold thy time was the time of Love: yea I entered into a Covenant with thee, and thou becameſt mine,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek. 16.6.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>This is a great myſtery: but I ſpeak concerning Chriſt and the Church, <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 5.32.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>—<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſocr.</hi> Orat. ad Demon.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Non requieſcit amor in quacun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſuperficiali adeptione a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mati, ſed quaerlt amatum perfectè habere, quaſi ad intima il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius perveniens, &amp;c. <bibl>Aqu. 1. 2ae. 28. a. 2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Matthew Symmons,</hi> in the yeare 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100079:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100079:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Philip</hi> Lord <hi>Wharton</hi> Baron of <hi>Wharton.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nexpreſſible &amp; uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable are thoſe cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all joyes, which proceed from the in-commings of Jeſus Chriſt upon the Soul, and her out-goings towards the Meſſiah againe; For is't not an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on earth, ſo to commerce with Chriſt? what, but this may bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to that Heaven above, where God gives out himſelfe in fulleſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, begetting like motions and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations in the glorified Saints? What gives the Saints mercies and morſels a right reliſh ſave this,<note n="a" place="margin">Mea non proſunt ſine me, nec tua proſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſine te, <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> Chriſts comming in upon as hand in hand with them, and making them good to us? and can any thing but his abſence mar the taſt of mercies? what
<pb facs="tcp:100079:3"/>ſhall I ſay? he that hath Chriſt wants not,<note n="*" place="margin">Is habet omnia, qui habet haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem omnia.</note> he that wants Chriſt inherits not what he ſeemeth to have. What's good to us without God?<note n="b" place="margin">Tolle meum et telle D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and what can be bad to us when we enjoy him?<note n="c" place="margin">Quid ſi ſine domo, et non ſine domino, ſine veſte, ſi non ſine fide, ſine ſibo, ſine lecto, et non ſine Chriſto?</note> what the Father ſaid of Joy, that may I ſay of the Joy-maker, and much more. There is ſo great a ſweetneſs in heavenly joy, that if one ſmall drop thereof ſhould fall into Hell, it would ſwallow up all the bitterneſs of that Tophet.<note n="d" place="margin">Tanta eſt dulcedo caele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis gaudij, ut ſi una guttula difflueret in infernum, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam a maritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni abſorberet. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt being had, makes bitter things ſweet, rough things ſmooth, and maſſie things light: Oh! what a Jeſus have we? do's not the Saints lothneſſe to bee rent from him, ſpeake out ſweetly what an one he is, to ſuch as ſit under his ſhade with delight?<note n="e" place="margin">Qui ſemel Chriſti dulce dinem guſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit deficile ab illo ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari ſuſtinet. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> Oh the power, purity, immenſity, and perenity of his love, mercie and goodneſs! how precious a thing is't to have, and to bee had of ſuch a precious Chriſt? Certainely time will diſcover it, 'twill be known at the time of his glorious appearance to judg the ſecrets of cloſeſt hearts, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:100079:3"/>to be honoured of all that believe: Of which number, I take the boldneſſe to repute your Honour, to be in the front among perſons of Honour. And what do I more then revive the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent report which hath gone forth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning your Honour, many yeares ſince?<note n="f" place="margin">Simulata non diu du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</note> what bad men ſay it skils not; ſure I am, good men ſpeak you a man of a moderate ſpirit, one who loves truth for the truths ſake: how you have done, &amp; do ſtill countenance the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly part of any party, I need not tel the World: but that which do's moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble your Honor, and make you moſt famous, is God's ſpeaking out his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of you, to your own ſoul; for that only <hi>is Circumciſion, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is of the heart, &amp; he is a right Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe praiſe is not of men only, but of God.</hi> Sir, I humbly preſent you with this ſmall Treatiſe, &amp; why ſhould I doubt of your favourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, in whoſe noble breaſt ſuch wiſedom &amp; ingenuity is found? Let him doubt that liſts; for I will not: the book is your honors, ſuch as it is, <hi>&amp;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:100079:4"/>if men meſtake not, it diſcovers hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſecret paſſages, and proceedings, betwixt Chriſt &amp; the Soul: &amp; what's more reviving to a ſpirituall perſon? In a word, this is but a ſmall acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of your Honours worth, yet future opportunities may cauſe to abound: goe on in wel-doing noble Patriot, and proſper, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile the differences of Saints, doe ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, love mercy, &amp; walk humbly with God; you may doe much good by your good example; For, as the Father ſpake, an Excellent Lord is better then an excellent Law. Thus ſhal you live ſo, as that you need not feare to die, and propagate Gods glory with your own name &amp; fame to future ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations. Now that it may be the lot of your honorable ſelf, with your noble Conſort, and all your Poſterity, to prize Chriſt, live in him, be ſaved by him, &amp; ſtated in everlaſting glory with him, ſhall be the deſire &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of him who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours humbly devoted to ſerve you in the things of Chriſt, SAM: MOORE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:100079:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>GOD</hi> whom we adore,<note place="margin">Thom 1<hi rend="sup">•</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te q. 20. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. 4.</note> is <hi>love,</hi> and what is beſt he loves moſt. His love is great to his worke, his people, his truth: but unto <hi>CHRIST</hi> it's above all, yea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the whole univerſe.<note place="margin">Raynerij Pantheolog: Tom, 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> p. 129.</note> The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any Good is, the greater 'tis belove'd. The more neare, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, like, excellent, laſting, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect any good is, by ſo much it's
<pb facs="tcp:100079:5"/>the greater. The <hi>LORD CHRIST</hi> in all theſe he's the <hi>neareſt</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> his humane nature is united to the divine,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.14. Mar. 16.19. Epheſ. 1.20, 21</note> hee ſits at the right hand of Majeſtie in glory: his <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſſe</hi> was emphatically twice witneſſed from Heaven,<note place="margin">Matth. 3.17.17. ch. 5. Iohn 16.23. Epheſ. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>This is my beloved Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed,</hi> and its for his ſake that wee are accepted. As for <hi>likeneſs,</hi> the foundation &amp; ſtrength of love (for whereſoever's the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>likeneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 1.3.</note> there's the greateſt love) Hee is the expreſſe Image of the Father, and his glory doth fully reſemble the Fathers glory for <hi>excellencie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 1.14.</note> it's his tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, hee's the chiefeſt among tenne thouſand,<note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 10. Iohn 1.14.</note> the only begotten <hi>Hebr. 1.6.</hi> Angels muſt adore him, and all men muſt give him equall honour with the Father;<note place="margin">Iohn 5.23.</note> Hee's the moſt <hi>excellent</hi> and <hi>laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> good without any ſeede of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,<note place="margin">Acts 2.31. Eſa 9.6.</note> the everlaſting Father, <hi>Hebr. 13.8.</hi> The ſame for ever, full of all <hi>perfections,</hi> all the
<pb facs="tcp:100079:5"/>treaſures of wiſdome and knowledg were in him, hee had all power,<note place="margin">Col. 2.3.</note> all things, <hi>Coloſſi. 1.19.</hi> all ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Coloſſians 2.9.</hi> even the fulneſſe of the Divinity,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.18. Iohn 3.35.</note> ſo that hee was and is altogether lovely, &amp; called the Fathers Well-beloved.</p>
            <p>Now notwithſtanding that CHRIST was the great and chiefe object of the FATHER'S love, the delight of his eye, and pleaſure of his ſoule, yet <hi>Him</hi> hath hee given unto the Sonnes of men for their <hi>life, John 10.10.</hi> For their <hi>light and learning,</hi> John <hi>8.12.</hi> Matth. <hi>11.29.</hi> For their <hi>livelihood,</hi> John <hi>6.51.</hi> For their <hi>redemption &amp; forgiveneſſe,</hi> Gal. <hi>3.13.</hi> Coloſſians <hi>1.14.</hi> For their <hi>peace and reconciliation,</hi> Eph. <hi>2.14.16.</hi> For their <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> Jerem. <hi>23.6.</hi> Rom. <hi>10.4.</hi> For their <hi>ſanctification, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>1.30.</hi> For their <hi>Covenant,</hi> Eſa <hi>42.6.</hi> For their <hi>Councellour,</hi> Eſay <hi>9.6.</hi> For their <hi>Conſolation,</hi> Hebrews <hi>2.25.</hi> For their <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,
<pb facs="tcp:100079:6"/>1</hi> Timothy <hi>2.5.</hi> For their <hi>Advocate, 1</hi> John <hi>2.1.</hi> For the <hi>Shepheard and Biſhop of their Soules, 1</hi> Peter <hi>2.25.</hi> For their <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> Eſay <hi>8.14.</hi> For their <hi>ſupply,</hi> John <hi>1.16.</hi> For their <hi>hope,</hi> Acts <hi>28.20.</hi> For their <hi>Foundation,</hi> Epheſ. <hi>2.20.</hi> For their <hi>Father,</hi> Eſay <hi>9.6.</hi> For their <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> Luke <hi>4.18.10.34.</hi> For their <hi>Salvation,</hi> Luke <hi>1.69.</hi> And for their <hi>Glory,</hi> Luke <hi>2.32.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Father therefore having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his dearely and deepely beloved Sonne unto us for ſuch ends and purpoſes, wee ſhould not doubt but that hee will be all theſe unto us. This Author in the firſt part of his Elaborate worke layeth open the yernings of Chriſts bowels towards all his languiſhing Friends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou be one of them, here's an <hi>Optick Glaſſe</hi> in which thou maiſt clearly ſee how the <hi>Heart and Bowels</hi> of CHRIST ſtand towards poore ſinners, and ſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:100079:6"/>wards thy ſelfe. What wouldſt thou have, which from him is not have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able? Doſt thou want life, light, maintenance, countenance: is't pardon, peace, purity thou wouldſt have? ſpeake, is't Righteouſneſſe, Councell, Comfort, friend-ſhip, ſafety thou needeſt? Art thou wounded and wanteſt healing? Art thou purſued by the Enemie, and wanteſt deliverance? is't grace or glory thou deſireſt? wouldſt thou have a word ſpoke for thee to the great KING of HEAVEN? have thy Cauſe pleaded for thee there? Is't reſolution, aſſurance, ſalvation thou ſigheſt and ſeekeſt after? In CHRIST who is <hi>All</hi> thou mayeſt finde all. Looke into this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> it ſweetely ſets out the <hi>Samaritaneſſe</hi> or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionateneſſe of Chriſt? it ſhews thee how readie he is to ſupply thy wants, and ſatisfie thy longings. Here thou ſhalt feele him drawing thy heart unto himſelfe, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee the ſight of glorious. My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries.
<pb facs="tcp:100079:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>It's our ignorance of Chriſts love and bowells, that fills us with feares, doubts, and jealouſies, that keepes us under bondage, and cauſeth us to reſt in ſhadowes and low things. The <hi>Author</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a good <hi>Remedie,</hi> hee hath opened Chriſts heart to thee, to draw thy heart to Him: and where ſhould Saints hearts be but where the heart of the Father is, and that's in Chriſt. His tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent worth affects him, his tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent worth and bowells ſhould affect us. Love to any thing chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the heart into the likeneſſe of the thing loved. If a man love earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, hee's <hi>vir terrenus,</hi> an earthly man, and his love is earthly; If a man love heavenly things, he's <hi>vir caeleſtis</hi> a heavenly man, and his worke is heavenly. Wouldſt thou bee a heavenly man, and love with heavenly love. This <hi>Worke</hi> will teach thee to love Chriſt, which will change thy heart into the nature of Chriſts heart, and ſo thy ſelfe and
<pb facs="tcp:100079:7"/>love will both become heavenly, &amp; the more heavenly thou art, the more fit for heavenly viſions, and glorious Myſteries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> this Treatiſe needs not my penne, it ſpeakes for it ſelfe, thou mayeſt accovnt it amongſt thy trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. It hath that in't is better then the Red earth of the world. The God of all truth teach thee by his ſpirit to know prize and practiſe all truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine if thou love the truth,</hi> W. Greenhil.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:100079:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100079:8"/>
            <head>A Table of ſome few Heads contained in this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Part. 1.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 1.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat's ment by loving, <hi>page. 1. &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How men are ſaid to be Chriſts owne: all are Chriſt's owne by right of dominion, for he's Lord of all. <hi>page 4.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Chriſts flock bis own by a ſix-fold right, <hi>page 4. 5. 6.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>End, what it ſignifies, <hi>p. 7. 8. 9.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>Chap. 2.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>THe love of Jeſus Chriſt what for kind,</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Sincere, without mixture.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Not ſelviſh, he loves not for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> Chaſt, undefiled.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> Full immenſe. <hi>page 11.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5.</hi> Free, and acts freely. <hi>p. 17.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <pb facs="tcp:100079:9"/>Chriſts love in what reſpects free. <hi>page 21. &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>6.</hi> A tractive drawing. <hi>p. 25. 26.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>7.</hi> Coerſive conſtraining. <hi>p. 27.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>8.</hi> Immutable, it cannot change, and why, in three particulars. <hi>p. 28.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 3.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>CHriſts love, what for degree.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Chriſts love's more then a friend, and how cleared by divers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. <hi>page 34, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Chriſt loves more then a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>page 39.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> More then a Husband. <hi>p. 40.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> Chriſt loves man more then he loves himſelfe, made evident in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular caſes. <hi>page 41, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5.</hi> The love betwixt Chriſt and chriſtians, greater then that love which is betwixt the Soule and the bodie. <hi>page 44.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>6.</hi> Chriſt loves man more then man loves Chriſt.</item>
                           <item>Three reaſons of that. <hi>Ibid, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 4.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>CHriſt's love, how diſcovered to his in two particulars.</item>
                           <item>
                              <pb facs="tcp:100079:9"/>
                              <hi>By words or works.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>By words, there are <hi>3.</hi> ſorts of Chriſts loue-diſcovering words. <hi>page 50. &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Chriſt prayes to his Father for Saints, and to what end.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> That their graces faile not. <hi>page 56. 57.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>And therein Chriſt peſwades the ſoule of two things to comfort &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> That hee ha's prayed for as bad as that ſoule can be.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> That he alwayes prevailed for what he prayed. <hi>page 58, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Hee prayes that their natures ſoile not. <hi>page 61.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Chriſt prayes to the Father in <hi>Sts.</hi> how, and in what ſence. <hi>page 62.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Chriſt putting words in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples mouths, and how. <hi>p. 65, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Chriſt's love, how diſcovered by workes.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> By doing for them.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> By ſuffering for them.</item>
                           <item>
                              <pb facs="tcp:100079:10"/>
                              <hi>3.</hi> By ſuffering with them. <hi>p. 74, 75.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Doing for them, and that <hi>1.</hi> in ſerving of them. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> In making his ſervices eaſie to them ſix wayes. <hi>p. 76, ctc.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Chriſt diſcovering his love by ſuffering for his. <hi>page 82.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The glory of the grace and favour of Jeſus Chriſt to his, how diſcovered in ſuffering for them, ſhewed in ſixe things. <hi>page 83, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The glory of that great worke glimps'd out by five things more. <hi>page 94, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Chriſt diſcovering heartie love to his followers by ſuffering with them, and how. <hi>page 103, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 5.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>TO what end Jeſus Chriſt ſets his love on loveleſſe ſinners and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoules.</item>
                           <item>Chriſt loves a poore polluted Soule to make it lovely in his owne bleſſed ſight, and unto his owne glorious ſelfe. <hi>page 111, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> To preſent his object blameleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:100079:10"/>both to himſelfe, and alſo to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>page 113.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How Chriſt differs from other lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in this reſpect. <hi>page 114.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>.</hi> To preſent his beloved ones ſpotleſſe, he ſets his love on ſoules to cleanſe, and ſanctifie them to his own and his Fathers uſe. <hi>p. 115.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> Chriſt loves to ſave the ſoule harmleſſe, preſerve and keepe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live. Satan loves to deſtroy: but Chriſt loves to ſave. <hi>page 116, 117</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Chriſts affection to his, calling for action from them for him. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> He's active for you, prayes for you, pleads for you at the Throne of grace night and day, againſt the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer of the Brethren. <hi>page 118.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Satans vaſſalls are active for him, and 'tis a moſt abhominable thing, and not to be paralell'd, that children of darkneſſe ſhould doe more for their Father, then do children of light for theirs. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:100079:11"/>
                  <label>PART. 2.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 1.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>CHriſt-like affections working to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Chriſt. <hi>page 1.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The riſe of this.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Divine love is active, and it acts towards Chriſt for fulneſſe. <hi>p. 2.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Chriſt is the Center to divine Love, and ariſing aloft in him it ha's reſt; and the ſoule it ſelfe is then a ſerene Spirit. <hi>page 3.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> Every thing hath its end, and moves towards that: love has its end too &amp; thitherward it moves. Grace has no other end but God &amp; glory. Love is a grace, and a great one, full of heavenly motion. <hi>page 4.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> Divine Love is the Divine nature, and cannot be confin'd in man who is but an heape of earth &amp; 'twill break forth upward till it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Glory. <hi>page 5.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5.</hi> Beſt intelects covet beſt objects, Chriſtians have the beſt intelects, therefore they love Chriſt. <hi>page 6.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Chriſt how the beſt object of Love
<pb facs="tcp:100079:11"/>Divine, made plaine in three parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>6.</hi> Divine Love goes out, workes towards Chriſt by a Divine inſtinct it aſcends upward: for it can doe no other. <hi>page 8.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>7.</hi> A ſpirituall ſoule is righteous, ſeeth 'tis a righteous thing to love Chriſt, ſee's ſome muſt love Chriſt, &amp; ſhee knowes none has more cauſe then ſhee. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>8</hi> A divine ſoule is reaſonable, ſeeth 'tis but reaſonable, to love him who loved her when ſhee had nothing in her worthy of love. <hi>page 9.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 2.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>CHriſtians ſhewing love to Chriſt and how, in twelve remarkable things. <hi>page 9, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 3.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>LOvers of Chriſt, how known.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Such as love Chriſt, ſee a motive in Chriſt, to ſtir up love (it
<pb facs="tcp:100079:12"/>being the emminencie of an object that ottracts love. <hi>page 29.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> A ſoul that loves Chriſt thirſts after his preſence, has never enough of his communion with her. <hi>p. 30, 31.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> One that loves Chriſt, feares to diſpreaſe him: true Lovers are loth to offend thoſe they prize and love. <hi>page 33.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4</hi> True love is of the perſon of Chriſt, were he without portion or priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. A Chriſt under ſhame as well as Glory, a Chriſt abas'd as well as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted. <hi>page 33, 34.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5.</hi> One that loves Chriſt would fain he, &amp; doe like Chriſt. <hi>p. 35, 36.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>6.</hi> They love Chriſts friends as the object of his delight. <hi>p. 37, 38.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP: 4.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>THe paſſage of Divine Love as it works towards Chriſt, may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, and how, cleared in ſix par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. <hi>page 39, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:100079:12"/>
                        <label>CHAP. 5.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>CHriſt keeping love alive in cbriſtians, and how, ſhewed in many particulars. <hi>page 50, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Incentives to love Chriſt, what, in ten particulars handled at large. <hi>page 59, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>PART. 3.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 1.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>VVHat things agree to make up a right ſigt naturall. <hi>p. 3.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Viſions of Heaven glorious, and why. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>They have in them God a glorious object, Chriſt a glorious medium, and a light ſuper-ſenſuall, ſupernaturall, and glorious too. <hi>page 4, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Right ſight of Chriſt, what.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> To ſee him as he is, <hi>p. 11, 12, 13.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Right ſight of Chriſt is experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall. <hi>page 14.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The good ariſing from ſuch a ſight of Chriſt, what, expreſs'd in four par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. <hi>page 4, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <pb facs="tcp:100079:13"/>The evill of the contrary, not to ſee Chriſt ezperimentally, clear'd by four things alſo. <hi>page 18, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> Right ſight of Chriſt, is to ſee Chriſt as a man is ſeene of Chriſt. <hi>p. 21.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How a Chriſtian is ſeene of Chriſt, in two particulars. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>A perſwaſion to looke up to Jeſus, and why. <hi>p. 23.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Incentives to that glorious work, what.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> All heires of everlaſting life long'd to ſee Chriſt before their death, and had their deſires. <hi>page 24.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The language of a Chriſt-leſs man or woman at the Judgement-day, what. <hi>page 25.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Mans neceſſity calls for this, hee muſt minde a Jeſus, ſee him by faith, for he wants him, and there is not another. <hi>page 26.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> A right ſight of Chriſt gives a right ſight of ſelfe, and ſelfes eſtate, it being moſt certain, that men never ſee themſelves ſo well as when they moſt ſee Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>page 28.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <pb facs="tcp:100079:13"/>Sight of Chriſt, what ſight of ſelfe it gives.</item>
                           <item>In him we may ſee what we have been, are, &amp; ſhall be. <hi>page 29, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> All right ſight of Chriſt has in't a ſuſtaining nature, a heart-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving vertue, a ſoule-reviving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, things of Heaven being all ſupporting, much more Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>page 34.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5.</hi> 'Twill encreaſe inward joy, a joy of heart, which excells the joy of harveſt. <hi>page 37, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>6.</hi> 'Twill ſtrengthen patience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the croſſe, and chſtaizement for Chriſt. <hi>page 40, 41, 42.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 2.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>THe likeneſſe betwixt the <hi>1.</hi> and <hi>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</hi> or the naturall and ſpiritual birth what, in eight particulars. <hi>page 43, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Four reaſons why men ſhould eſteem it a greater priviledge to bee borne twice, then to be borne but once. <hi>page 56, 57, 58, 59.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How God brings in, and brings up returning ſinners.</item>
                           <item>
                              <pb facs="tcp:100079:14"/>
                              <hi>1.</hi> He principles them.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Acts them.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> builds them.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> Conſtrmes them. <hi>page 60.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How God principles thoſe bee will ſave. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Chriſt's act by which he drawes out thoſe principles, what.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Illumination. <hi>page 61.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>What work light makes in a darke Soule. <hi>Ibid, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Humiliation. <hi>page 63.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How Chriſt humbles men kindly. <hi>page 64, 65.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>To what end Chriſt humbles, layes low choſen veſſels. <hi>page 66.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How Chriſt builds Chriſtians.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> by keeping them and all their graces in continuall action. <hi>p. 74.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> By infuſing ſtrength ſuitable to oppoſition. <hi>page 75.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>What Chriſt in building helps his people to live above, whilſt they live in the body.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Above corruption.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Above temptations.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> Above gracious evidences.</item>
                           <item>
                              <pb facs="tcp:100079:14"/>
                              <hi>4.</hi> Above glorious manifeſtations of his Fathers love, &amp; how. <hi>page 79. &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Chriſt confirms his, &amp; how. <hi>p. 87.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The effects of ſuch ſtability of heart in that reſpect, what. <hi>page 88.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The faith of Saints concerning this, what. <hi>page 90.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 3.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>CItizens of heaven are ſtrangers here.</item>
                           <item>What it is to be a ſtranger here, <hi>4.</hi> particulars of that. <hi>page 92, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Whence it is that Chriſt lets his live ſo far from home, that God ſo kind a Father, puts his children into ſuch an unkind world. <hi>page 105.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> To put a difference betwixt Earth and Heaven.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> To glimpſe out Glory to a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe people. <hi>page 107.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> To ſave others alive. <hi>page 108, 109.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> To diſpoſe them for higher things, and how, <hi>page 110, 111.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5.</hi> That grace might have a being as well as glory. <hi>page 112.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <pb facs="tcp:100079:15"/>Strangers on Earth how knowne.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> By the price they put on glory, <hi>&amp;</hi> the thoughts they have of Heaven. <hi>page 113.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> By the language they ſpeak. <hi>page 114.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> A ſtrangers mind &amp; motion is home-ward, though he lacks nothing. <hi>page 116, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The practice of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>
                              </hi> making good this principle, and how. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> Strangers in a ſtrange Land content themſelves only with things needful. <hi>page 119.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5</hi> Strangers ingage not themſelves too much in the affairs of the natives of ſtrange Lands. <hi>page 123.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How little cauſe Saints have to love this ſtrange Land, or be loth to leave it.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Till then they're far from their beſt friends &amp; chiefeſt favours, they are in a farre Countrey, whilſt from their Fathers houſe. <hi>page 124.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Other conſiderations to looſen the Saints from the world. <hi>p. 125, 126.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> They ſhould not love it, be loth
<pb facs="tcp:100079:15"/>to leave it: for till then they'l be foi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, vex'd &amp; ſoil'd with filthy ſins. <hi>page 127.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Saints being ſtrangers, what they ſhould be, and doe, whilſt ranging through this earthly region. <hi>p. 128.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 4.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>SAints have their appointed time of change.</item>
                           <item>To be changed, what.</item>
                           <item>'Tis to have a different manner of being: 'tis the ceſſation of a perſon or thing from being what it once was. <hi>page 130.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The ſundry ſorts of changes, what in <hi>3</hi> particulars. <hi>p. 131, 132, 133. 134</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>To be gloriouſly chang'd, what. <hi>page 135.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>A three-fold imployment for Saints in order to a diſpoſing of them for their laſt, greateſt, and beſt of chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <hi>page 136, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Saints have need to be chang'd, two reaſons of that. <hi>p. 140, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 5.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>GLory, what. <hi>page 182.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>What things concur to make up
<pb facs="tcp:100079:16"/>everlaſting glory. <hi>page 183, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>To be glorified compleatly, what. <hi>page 196, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The glory of the ſoule in heaven, what. <hi>page 197, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>What the glory of the body ſhall bee in the Kingdome of heaven. <hi>page 199, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>What the glory is that ſoule &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhall poſſeſſe joyntly. <hi>p. 206, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The adjuncts of glory, what. <hi>page 224, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>The Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Part 1.</label>
PAge 1. l. 3. r. acts are, p. 6. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 8. l. 12. r. p. 8. l. 2. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 3. l. 10. r. uſuall, p. 30. r. crucis, p. 34. l. 11. r. meted p. 55. l. r. his. p. 65. l. 25. r. on, p 67. r. riſiſſe, p. 80. r. rebellis, p. 93. r. niſi, p. 114. l. 10. r. ſhee, p. 65. r. nobis, p. 73. <hi>murorum,</hi> p. 30. r. <hi>numero,</hi> p. 42. r. <hi>Aethyopiſſam quandam,</hi> p. 56. l. 12 r. <hi>promiſory,</hi> p. 80. r. <hi>protegentis,</hi> &amp; dele via.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Part 2.</label>
Page 33. r. <hi>in cum.</hi> p. 62. r. perfecte, p. 56. r. abſentia, p. 68. r. judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant. p. 3. l. 19. r. Center, p. 56. l. 21. r. Ieopardy, p. 59. l. 26. r. Iſhmael.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Part 3.</label>
Page 8. l. 7. r &amp;, p. 12. l. t. r he, p. 14. l. 2. r. thy, p. 34. l. 23. r. affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, p. 47. l. 8. r. loth, p. 46. l. 2. dele to, p. 54. l. 21. r. its ſo. l. 22. p. 61. l. 24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. this, p. 80. l. 20. r. doubtfull, p. 106. l. 8. r. wearie, p. 116. l. r. r. thoſe, p. 52 l. 14. r. ſoule, p. 158. l. 3. r hearing, p. 182. l. 10. dele to, p. 183. l. 1 dele where, p. 206. l. 4. r. eternally, p. 167. r. <hi>exoſumer, eſſe Chriſto.</hi> p. 212. r. <hi>Coacreatae.</hi> Some other leſſer faults there bee, which the Printer &amp; Corrector deſire the Reader to relieve with his penne.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100079:16"/>
            <head>THE YERNINGS OF Chriſts bowells to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his languiſhing FRIENDS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 13.1.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </bibl>
               <q>Having loved his own which were in the world, he loved them unto the end.<note n="*" place="margin">Quum dilex iſſet ſuos qui erant, &amp;c. <hi>Montanus.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> diligo &amp; ſimpliciter amo.</note>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the ſence of the words, and their uſefulneſſe unto all Chriſt-obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here affection is the ſpring of action, and operation, love is perfect to perpetui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Chriſt act's as he is, he's with out end, ſo is his love. Things of Heaven are all laſting, everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100079:17"/>you may gueſſe at their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, but never at their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
               <p>The word in the originall<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> properly ſignifies, to love ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by adhering to it with the mind and heart:<note n="a" place="margin">Suidas, ſeu aliquem amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re complector &amp; cum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo amiciti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am colo: <hi>as</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2 10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.24. <hi>cha.</hi> 22.37. <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.21. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſo to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ſatisfied with it, as that a man deſires nothing elſe<note n="b" place="margin">Me aut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabis, aut quo conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſum dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <hi>Cic. Others ſay 'tis more then</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>as com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> valdè, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſco: quae enim diligimus in iis acquieſcimus. <hi>Alſied-</hi> in <hi>Lexic.</hi> ſigniſicat contentum eſſe acquieſcere, <hi>Caſaub.</hi> in <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.21. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> apud LXX. <hi>Interpretes,</hi> non ſemper pro diligere, ſed &amp; pro amicis blandiſque verbis compellare, &amp; laudare, ſumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ut <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.14.2. <hi>Paral.</hi> 18.2.</note>. 'Tis hearty love, Chriſt is ſaid* <hi>to love the young man: viz.</hi> hee ſpake friendly to him, and dealt gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with him, as the word there imports. Bleſſed <hi>Meſsiah</hi> the Saints Saviour, at his laſt depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from them; adhered to them with all his might, ſoule, mind, and ſtrength: and was ſo fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with them, tooke ſuch great content in them, as that he deſir'd no other portion beſides them. And thus ſpeaking ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100079:17"/>and kindly to them, call's them his owne<note n="c" place="margin">Peculiaritèr deſtinatus, <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 5. peculiaris, ab <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, cujus eſt certa quaedam, &amp; minime cum caeteris communis idea, <hi>Cajet.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 11.6. vide <hi>Bezam</hi> in loc. <hi>The Lord Chriſt is call'd</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>God's owne Sonne,</hi> quod ſit filius Dei per aeternam generatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note>, as being his peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar portion.</p>
               <p>His owne, every word of Chriſt hath its weight, every word drop's ſweetneſſe as the hony combe. Chriſtians you ſee your bleſſed lot, you are Chriſt's owne, and Chriſt is your owne. This comfortable kind of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſtians is very uſefull in Scripture; as Jeſus Chriſt is the faithfull's owne, ſo the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are Jeſus Chriſt's own, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4. God is termed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the beleeving Chriſtians <hi>owne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, he ſhall be holden up by his owne Maſter; for God is able to make him ſtand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſtians! have you had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the powerfull wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of Gods love towards you, and on your Spirits? and doe you feare a finall falling, a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, or totall declining from Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and his ſweeteſt wayes of ſoule-raviſhing contentments?
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100079:18"/>Remember God's your owne, he both can, and will make you ſtand. <hi>Thoſe that truſt in the Lord, ſhall be as Mount Sion, that ſhall never be removed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In generall conſider, Chriſt hath and may claime title to all by a right of dominion, and ſo all then are Chriſts owne, as he's Lord of all creatures. But Chriſts flock are his owne thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By right of donation, God hath given ſome to Chriſt, and what's more a mans owne, then that which is given him? The great God gives great gifts like himſelfe: millions of ſoules had Chriſt given him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By right of purchaſe and Redemption, Jeſus Chriſt hath bought ſome, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. given <hi>precious,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Fortaſis epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetum, (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſa) non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nullum habet reſpectum ad pretium ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, &amp; merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium ejus-<hi>Lorinus,</hi> in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</note> 
                  <hi>bloud</hi> for ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſoules, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>he gave himſelfe for us:</hi> not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a ranſome, but alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a counter-ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for all our ſinnes. Oh thou
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100079:18"/>man of God, ponder theſe things well in thine owne minde. Chriſt <hi>gave his owne ſelfe</hi> for thy ſelfe, and art not thou then his owne? canſt thou then have the heart to act ſuch a part of unkindneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him as to ſerve thy ſelfe? <hi>God forbid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. By right of conqueſt, hee hath conquerd ſome with kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and overcome ſome with unexpreſſible love, he hath ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued them to himſelfe, and their ſinnes with Satan downe to the duſt, and therefore they may well be his, and ſhall not he have the greateſt ſhare in them? May not Chriſt ſay to a ſubjected ſoule, as <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Philemon: thou oweſt mee even thine owne ſelfe?</hi> Me think's the ſoule ſhould thus reply, yea Lord, and take me and all mine, for thine owne uſe, my ſoule, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſtrength, what I am, or may be, for it's thine owne.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By right of ſtipulation,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8.</note> or Covenant-making, <hi>I entred into
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100079:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>a Covenant with thee and thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cameſt mine:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>I entred into a contract, or bargain with thee,</hi> and ſhall not the Lord have his bargaine?</p>
               <p n="5">5. By right of a gracious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, ſome are ſweetly ſanctified to the uſe of Chriſt, to the ſervice of Chriſt and no other. <hi>The Lord hath ſet apart him that's godly for himſelfe.</hi> Some are <hi>veſſells of honour, fitted</hi> for their Maſters uſe, <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.19.22. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 4.3.</p>
               <p n="6">6. A Beleever is Chriſts owne, by a right of Regeneration, as he's <hi>begotten againe,</hi> in and after Chriſt's owne Image. God the Father, through Chriſt by his Spirit, hath <hi>begotten them againe</hi> into Chriſt's owne likeneſſe. The firſt <hi>Adam begat a ſonne in his own likeneſſe, after his owne Image</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> vel ut ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui volunt, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. genuit ſecundum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guram ſuam.</note>, the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> did ſo too. And being <hi>begotten againe</hi> in his like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as children truly like their owne heavenly Father: they are truly and properly call'd his <hi>own</hi> children.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100079:19"/>End ſignifies diverſly<note n="f" place="margin">Deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> 
                     <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> tandem <hi>Beza,</hi> ad finem uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> i. e. indeſinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <hi>Piſcator.</hi> Omni tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hoc eſt ſemper perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuò.</note>. Firſt the continuation of a thing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.17, 18. <hi>He ſhall regard the prayer of the deſtitute, and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it, this ſhall be written for the Generations to come,</hi> i. e. <hi>inperpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum</hi> for ever. <hi>Iſal.</hi> 9.7. <hi>The Lord ſhall endure for ever.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">* Aſſiduè <hi>Druſius, this ſence from the place, Nazian.</hi> perpetuò vulg. lat. in finem.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Where the <hi>Chaldie</hi> hath it <hi>in ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum,</hi> the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Chriſt loves his owne with <hi>an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſtians! doe yee ſometimes doubt, through miſapprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and miſtakes? 'tis without cauſe given on Jeſus his part. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, end's put ſometimes for extremitie, as miſery ſorrow, and ſuffering, is the end of ſinning; death is the end of life, ſorrow, miſery, and death, is mans extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. <hi>Meſsiah loves his owne,</hi> in all their extremities.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Sometimes it ſignifies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>The Graecians ſignificantly call end and perfection by one and the ſame terme,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſignificat tam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio, quam finem facio, fineo, obeo, <hi>or</hi> conſummo, benevertit ergo Poeta, Phyllirides pucrum, citharâ perfecit <hi>Achillem.</hi>
                  </note> alſo as growth is the end
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100079:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>of youth, <hi>i. e.</hi> the perfection of youth.</p>
               <p>Glory is the end of grace, <hi>viz.</hi> the perfection of grace, for grace is initiall glory, glory begun: a chriſtian, that is ſanctified, ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſet apart to the Lords uſe, begin's to live the life of glory even here in the Kingdome of grace. Grace is glory incho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, Glory is grace conſummate.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Sometimes the ſcope, or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall cauſe<note n="h" place="margin">Scopus, ſeu, cauſa finalis, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. ſignificat eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am exitus ſeu eventus. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. <hi>James</hi> 5.11.</note> of things: Chriſt is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the end of the Law, for righteouſneſſe to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that beleeveth,</hi> viz. that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of holineſſe, and that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite righteouſneſſe, with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt fulnes, which the <hi>moſt holy God,</hi> and his <hi>moſt holy Law</hi> aimed at: and which is more, he did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly anſwer, and fully ſatisfie the exacteſt mandates, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, of the ſame ſtricteſt Law for every beleeving ſoule. Chriſt loves his to the ſame end the Law aimes at, <hi>viz.</hi> to make them
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100079:20"/>holy, and <hi>preſent them blameleſſe, before his Father with exceeding great joy.</hi> Ah Lord! who is wiſe, and ſee'th not ſtrength of <hi>love ſhed abroad</hi> by the Spirit in the hearts of thine?</p>
               <p>In this text it's put for death onley, <hi>he loved them to the end, i. e.</hi> to the death, not that death could put an end to Chriſt's love, by which he adhered, and doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to his.<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chriſt's love's immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall.</hi> Mors igitur non finit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</note> Death only ends mortall things, Death was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to breake the bands of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which were betwixt head and members, Chriſt and chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that could not deſtroy the power of union betwixt him and his, for how could death put an end to that which tooke away its ſting from it? Chriſt's love to his ſubdu'd him to incounter with Death, Hell, and the grave, who is now triumphing over all <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and Powers.</hi> The ſence then may be ſuch as this, that it put an end to his terrene, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100079:21"/>mortall life, and converſation, amongſt them here<note n="i" place="margin">Mors voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> non quòd omnia in morte, &amp; cum morte, ſiniantur, quia etiam de Chriſti mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, haec ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellatio uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patur, ſed quia terrenae &amp; mortali huic vitae, ac mundanae converſationi finem impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. <hi>Gerh.</hi> in locum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.1.</note>, and ſo hee loved them to the end of that courſe he ſteered with them here in the body. For 'twas come to this, that bodily preſence muſt now for a time be ſuſpended, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall fellowſhip certainly end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though very ſad newes to the hearts of his followers, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, yet all in love. Now he and his muſt be taken aſunder for a time, that they may be joyn'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againe, when time ſhall be no more. Thus <hi>when Jeſus knew the houre was come, that he ſhould depart out of this world to the Father, loving his owne he loved them,</hi> did cleave to them, even <hi>unto the end.</hi> The note from the words then may be ſuch as this. Chriſt loves chriſtians with a laſting, yea, an everlaſting love. <hi>Loving he loved and that to the end.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the nature of Chriſts Love.</head>
               <head type="sub">ALl motion is as the propenſion is,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100079:21"/>in the primum mobile, firſt moover.</head>
               <head type="sub">God is good, that's his nature, and he does good, that's the fruit of his peereleſſe goodneſſe, ſome deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have their bounds, but can you limit limitleſſe love?</head>
               <head type="sub">Chriſt's love is ſuch as himſelf is, full of all amiable glory: Chriſt's good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is not hid, we'le ſhew you firſt what it is, &amp; then the degrees on't.</head>
               <p>FIrſt Chriſt's love unto belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſoules, is for kind, ſincere, without mixture, a love without hatred, a liking without loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The ſonnes of men love with a mixed kind of love, there love hath ſome ingredient of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in it, which is ſoone diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered as occaſion ſerves. But the Sonne of God doth not ſo, is not ſo eaſily incenſed againſt thoſe he loves. Men hate the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of men, men when they are offended with the failings of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, doe forthwith, if they can, avenge themſelves: upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of thoſe by whom they are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100079:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>injured. But Chriſt takes venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance onely on ſinne, <hi>thou waſt a a God that forgaveſt them,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>though thou took'ſt venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on their inventions, Pſ.</hi> 99.8. Chriſt ſeeth himſelfe in chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans whom ſinne cannot deſtroy, he loves them for <hi>his owne ſake,</hi> hee accepts what's his, forgives what's theirs<note n="k" place="margin">Accipit ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, remittit tuum.</note>.</p>
               <p>Chriſt loves them becauſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is in them, and cannot loath them, for as hee cannot deny himſelfe, ſo neither can he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not ſelf-iſh, he loves not for rewards, if hee did, where ſhould he have them? other lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers aime at themſelves ſo much in loving others, as that oft-times they looſe themſelves in ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love, every man had rather be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to himſelfe then to another<note n="l" place="margin">Omnes ſibi melius eſſe malle quam alteri. <hi>Teren.</hi>
                  </note>. But Chriſt may truly ſay to his friends,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> did to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians. I ſeeke not yours but you;</hi> he's better to others then to himſelfe,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100079:22"/>ſuffer'd for many, but brought not ſuffering on any. Chriſt ſeeks not himſelfe; but thy ſelfe. Oh ſoule! hath hee any dowry with thee, when hee makes thee his ſpouſe? thou haſt nothing of thine owne to give him but thy ſinne: thou art nothing of thy ſelfe for him, but a heape of earth, ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, a meere <hi>rudis indigeſtaque moles,</hi> what is there in thee that ſo great a Majeſtie ſhould ſet his love upon thee? Or if there were ſomething in thee for Chriſt, as there is not, is he a gainer by it? can he receive that hee doth not poſſeſſe already<note n="m" place="margin">Talis eſt dilectio Dei erga nos, quatenus ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil boni à no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ipſi pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè accreſcit. Ameſius de conſc. &amp; ejus caſ. l. 4. c. 10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15.</note>? Nay are not we receivers and he a giver?</p>
               <p>Conſider his love, he is what hee is <hi>for your ſakes,</hi> you ſonnes of love and choſen friends, <hi>all things are for your ſakes, that the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant grace might, through the thanks-giving of many, redound to the glory of God.</hi> Speaking in the antecedent verſe of <hi>Chriſts reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, he died and was buried for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100079:23"/>you,</hi> and is <hi>riſen againe for your ſakes.</hi> Loe, ſee an infallible cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a non-ſelfe lover! <hi>hee ſanctified himſelfe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.19.</note> ſet apart him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for you, herein is the praiſe of his grace; that <hi>when hee was rich he became poore for your ſakes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9.</note> 
                  <hi>that you through his poverty might be made rich.</hi> And <hi>you know it</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> God hath made you to know it; that this was his free Grace: that he <hi>ſought not yours, but you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is chaſte, undefiled, whence thoſe Epithites, <hi>Love, Dove, undefiled ſiſter, Cant.</hi> 5.2. to take away the ſuſpition of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſte love<note n="n" place="margin">Ut tollere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſuſpicio foedi amoris. <hi>Hirom.</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Iovinian, lib. 1. Tam à me pudica eſt, quam mea ſi ſoror ſit, <hi>Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi>
                  </note>: for this name ſiſter implies a deteſtation of all fleſhly impurity. <hi>Ignatius</hi> that holy Martyr call'd Chriſt by this name, my love, ſaith he, was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifi'd: carnall eares, eyes, and hearts, take in carnall conceits of Chriſts love, ſport themſelves with the Letter: but the ſeries of the letter is nothing ſerious, as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100079:23"/>
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> notes<note n="o" place="margin">Nihil enim ſerium habet literae ſeries. <hi>Ber.</hi> ſup. Cant. ſerm. 6.</note>. And therefore let the ſpirituall Spouſe of Chriſt, conceive ſpiritually of ſuch heavenly and ſweet expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of love<note n="p" place="margin">ut ſpiritualis audi ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litèr amatoria verba cantai, <hi>Orig.</hi> in <hi>Cant.</hi> hom. 2. Non virum &amp; foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minam, ſed verbum &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimam ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as. <hi>Ber.</hi> ibid.</note>: view not ſo much the outſide of the phraſe as the inſide of the ſence. He loves you chriſtians with a pure, perfect and undefiled love. Breake the bone of the letter and thou ſhalt find the marrow of the ſence<note n="q" place="margin">frange os li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terae, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venies me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dullam intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentiae. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Bleſ.</hi> Ser. 3.</note> 'Tis the property of beaſts to live on chaffe, of men to live on corne,<note n="r" place="margin">Fumento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt paleis hominum fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis veſci. <hi>Greg.</hi> proeam. in <hi>Cant.</hi>
                  </note> goe forth therefore from the ſence of the fleſh to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the mind<note n="ſ" place="margin">Egredimini deſenſu car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, ad intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. <hi>Ber</hi> in <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha.</hi> ſer. 2.</note>.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, It is full, <hi>in him all fulneſſe dwells</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Omne imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum redigitur ad perfectum, ſi nos ad Chriſtum, à quo om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis perfectio deſcendit. Savanat. Expoſ. 4. orat. Domini.</note>, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19. it hath <hi>height, and depth, length and breadth, in it: of his fulneſſe we receive grace for grace, Joh.</hi> 1.16. Chriſt had not grace by meaſure, in this he was <hi>anointed above his fellowes:</hi> who had grace only by meaſure. There is not onely in Chriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a ſufficiency, but alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100079:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>redundancie of grace, as the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher diſtinguiſheth, for this the Apoſtle affirmeth, he hath a <hi>ſufficiency and Fulneſſe of grace,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in every neceſsity,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>at every time,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of every grace.</hi> fulneſſe is for emptineſſe, and 'tis the joy and glory of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, my friends, that their ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is in their head.</p>
               <p>That 'tis where 'tis ſafe, and from whence it flowes fully and ſweetly into their ſoules. Chriſt is the well, thou beleeving ſoule let downe thy bucket, and drinke and live. Chriſt loues out of the abundance of goodneſſe, becauſe hee expects no profit out of us: <hi>for wee are unprofitable ſervants:</hi> but our love to him is out of the want of goodneſſe, becauſe wee ſtand in need of God<note n="u" place="margin">Sed ejus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor ex abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantia bonita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, quia nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum è nobis commodum expectat; nos enim ſervi ſumus inutiles Deo, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.10. noſtra autem erga eum eſt ex indigentia, quia Deo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digemus. <hi>Ameſius</hi> in medul. l. 2. cap. 7.</note>. Chriſt hath in him the fulneſſe of a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, give he ne're ſo much out
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100079:24"/>to us: he hath ne'r the leſſe in himſelfe hee is an inexhauſtible well-ſpring of life, he is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly full in himſelfe, and for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: but alſo communicatively unto others.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Chriſt's love is free<note n="vv" place="margin">Non habet quo intret gratia, ubi meritum oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupavit. <hi>Bern. in cant. ſerm.</hi> 67.</note>, acts freely in diſpenſation to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpirituall ſoule, <hi>I will love them freely, Hoſ.</hi> 14.4.2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. men oft-times doe not the good they might, when they have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity; but Chriſt ſeeks for an opportunity, waites for it, <hi>goes about doing good.</hi> You have ſome lovers that will love; but then there is this defect in their love, it is onely extorted from them, by kindneſſes and curteſies done to them, and received by them, from them whom they affect: but can you force love from Chriſt<note n="x" place="margin">Omnia quae de Chriſto le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geris non ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate, ſed ſponte facta reperies <hi>Orig. in gen. hom.</hi> 8. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.8.</note>? if you could you need not: for he love's freely, he's free enough, <hi>freely you have received.</hi> Chriſt's bowells yerne fully, all his gifts are given freely, come from him
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100079:25"/>freely.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24.</note> Juſtification comes free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Sanctification, Glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on freely, <hi>The Lord did not ſet his love upon you, nor chooſe you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you were more in number then any people: for ye were the feweſt of all people; but becauſe he loved you, Deut</hi> 7.7, 8. he did it not from any motive ariſing from you; for there was nothing in you to draw and kindle his love: but he did it becauſe he did it<note n="y" place="margin">Amat quia amat <hi>Bern.</hi>
                  </note>. He chooſeth none worthy of himſelfe, but by chooſing them makes them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy<note n="z" place="margin">Nullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eligit dignum, ſed eligendo effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit dignum. <hi>Aug. cont. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, Pelag. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note>. Theſe things demonſtrate freenes of grace to be in Chriſt, &amp; to flow from him into beleevers.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in that when hee ſets his love upon a ſoule, hee finds no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in that ſoule worthy of love: he findes much matter of loathing; but nothing that's mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of love, as an object fit and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for Divine love to faſten up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. When a poore ſinner lieth buried in pollutions, and fleſhly defilements, and hath no cauſe in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100079:25"/>him moving Chriſt to love, hee makes lovely, and then loves, though he findes that ſoule loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. from the third to the eight.</p>
               <p>Chriſt himſelfe became un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.2.</note> that hee might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cover their uncomely parts with his comelineſſe, <hi>he was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out forms and comelineſſe, and when men ſaw him, there was no beauty that they ſhould deſire him:</hi> this he was for your ſakes. Chriſt doth as wee our ſelves doe, <hi>upon thoſe members that we thinke to be leſſe honourable;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.23.</note> 
                  <hi>even on them we beſtow more abundant honour, and on our uncomely parts, more abundant come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</hi> Chriſt beſtoweth on the more uncomely ſinner, receiving him, the more abundant come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe: ſo that the greateſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, make the moſt gracious Saints. <hi>Paul</hi> was once, one of the <hi>chiefe of</hi> ſinners, the worſt of men: but after the Lord Chriſt in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy look'd on him: and wrought
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100079:26"/>kindly upon his Spirit, he became then one of the beſt of men; <hi>in labours more abundant</hi> for Chriſt <hi>then all others.</hi> Oft-times it falls out, that ſuch as are moſt rejected of men, are moſt reſpected of God. <hi>A lame Mephiboſheth, a halting creeple, a blind Phariſee, a leprous Samaritan,</hi> Luk. 12 16. an <hi>ulcerous Lazarus, a woman with a bloudy iſſue,</hi> Mark. 5.34. Perſons uncleane, and contemptible, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of diſdaine in the eyes of men<note n="a" place="margin">Non deſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris animus foedatur: ſed pulchritudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne animi corpus orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Senec.</hi>
                  </note>, he hath choſen alſo perſons of meane employments, as <hi>Amos a heards-man, Gideon a thraſher, Abel a ſhepheard, Noah a husbandman, Joſeph a Carpenter, Peter and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew fiſhers; James and John fiſhers, mending their nets were called, and a Jaylor with many others of this world's poore, who were rich in Faith, when choſen. Mary a harlot, Rachel a harlot, Paul</hi> a blaſphemer: ſome of all ſorts of ſinners have been and ſhall bee ſaved through the riches of his grace: yet God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100079:26"/>you ſhould ſinne that Grace may abound: doe not ſo ſinne againſt Chriſt; for if yee are Chriſt's, yee dare not.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in that he comes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a loveleſſe ſinner, and ſinfull ſoule, unſeene, unſought, and not deſired.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Unſeen, a man by nature is borne ſpiritually blind, hee ſee's not his owne wants, nor Chriſt's worth: the ſinfulneſſe of ſinne, nor the goodneſſe and ſweetneſſe of a Saviour: he ſee's not his owne miſery, perceives not the nature of the Lords mercy, he conſiders not his ſpirituall penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Chriſt comes upon the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of men inviſibly, unſeen, which ſhewes 'tis from free love: and that no proviſion can be made in any ſoule for the Lord Chriſt; but what hee brings along with him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, unſought, <hi>I am found of them that ſought me not; I ſaid behold me, behold me, to a people that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100079:27"/>was not called by my name,</hi> I ſaiah 65.1. <hi>viz.</hi> the heathen Gentiles, that could not ſeek, nor grope for, and after Jeſus Chriſt: a people that had not ſo much as a good name, to commend them (if it were poſſible) to Chriſt, much leſſe good natures. What then moved this bleſſed lover to ſet his love upon them? was it any thing they had for Chriſt, or to bring unto Chriſt? ſurely no. What then? 'twas the freeneſſe of Chriſt's will to doe good, that moved him to love freely. <hi>I will have mercy on whom I will have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> that's his determination. He's unſought, not ſought of them: but they are ſought of him. He's the ſeeker before converſion, (if there be any) which muſt needs be, if there be any reconcilement betwixt God and the ſoule.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>I am come to ſeek and to ſave that which is loſt.</hi> Chriſt ſeekes us before we doe or can ſeek him, we are loſt till then. Chriſt elects us alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100079:27"/>we can elect him:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.6.</note> 
                  <hi>you have not choſen mee</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>but I have choſen you:</hi> you ſee then Chriſt's love is free, and acts freely to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſuch as he will ſave.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Chriſt workes on the ſoules of men when not deſired, naturall men doe not know him, are not acquainted with him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 21.14.</note> his outgoings and incommings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them,<note n="b" place="margin">Scientia non habet inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum praeter ignorantem. Tolerabilior eſt paena vive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non poſſe, quam neſcite. <hi>Senec.</hi>
                  </note> they are enemies to the knowledge of a crucified Chriſt, and it is certaine there can be no deſire of unknowne ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: <hi>When we ſhall ſee him, there is no beauty that we ſhould deſire him, Iſaiah</hi> 53.2. The Prophet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts what carnall and naturall men would thinke, and conceive of Chriſt in their naturall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. If men ſee no beauty in Chriſt, no lovelineſſe and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in him, it is impoſſible they ſhould deſire him: for 'tis the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, luſter, and beauty of an object, that ſtrengthneth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires towards it, and fixeth the eye
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100079:28"/>of the intellect, the underſtanding upon it. Chriſt loves when not deſired, and therefore <hi>loves freely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, it's free for that it acts againſt repulſes<note n="*" place="margin">Chriſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times workes his workes on croſſe and perverſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: ſome Chriſtians have as croſſe ſpirits by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as can be in nature found: yet he chooſeth them when better, and ſweeter na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd. Ah Lord! what a great myſtery of godlineſſe is this?</note>, love can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be acquired by doing inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, deſerved by repulſes: and therefore free, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 65.23. <hi>I ſtretched out my hands all the day, to a rebellious people: a people that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh me to anger continually to my face.</hi> Was this the way to be belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of God? much leſſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure love: was it not the direct way to be ruined, ſtripped of God, Chriſt and all goodneſſe<note n="c" place="margin">Maium eſt agere quod prohibetur, ſed agere quia prohibetur peſſimum. <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.14.</note>? and yet you ſee he ſtretcheth out his arme, he not onely put's it forth; but alſo ſtretcheth it forth, as if he ſhould ſtraine himſelfe, to embrace thoſe that will come out of darkneſſe, into marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous light and liberty. Is not this grace free? what ſo free as this? Naturall men before Chriſt's Spirit comes into their hearts, in powerfull workings;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100079:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>they cry out: <hi>Lord depart from us, we will none of thy wayes:</hi> and did not the Lord in love, draw nigh to them, where were they? what would their end be? Chriſt's love is free.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, it's attractive, it's a draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing love, <hi>I have drawne thee with loving kindneſſe, Jer.</hi> 31.3. Some lovers love dearely: but cannot draw their objects nigh to them: they love but are not loved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: their love is fruitleſſe: But Chriſt's love begets love, love like it ſelfe. <hi>Draw me ſaith the Spouſe, and I will runne after thee.</hi> Chriſt could draw teares from <hi>Peters</hi> eyes, with one looke of love, and he <hi>wept bitterly</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Petrus,</hi> tunc flevit quando in cum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus reſpexit. <hi>Bern.</hi> de mod. benè viv. ſer. 10. <hi>Petrus</hi> flevit &amp; tacuit, quia quod defleri ſolet, non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let excuſari, &amp; quod defendi non poteſt. ablui poteſt. <hi>Ambr.</hi> 10.3. ſer. 46. <hi>Greg. Homil.</hi> 30. in Evang.</note> ſaith the Text. Chriſt's love is <hi>magnes amoris</hi> the Loadſtone of love. it drawes Iron hearts to it, and makes them melt before the Sun of Righteouſneſſe: when it ſhines upon them ſweetly.</p>
               <p>Chriſt's love is a heart ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing love, he can ſnatch a <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100079:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>into the <hi>third heavens,</hi> and fill him with joy, peace and glory inviſibly: he can ſo wrap him up in the thoughts of his love, and fruits of his goodneſſe, as that the man is loſt in God, is in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie, cannot tell you what hee ha's ſeen, felt, or heard. Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirits! you can ſay Amen to the truth of theſe things. Ha's not his love ſerved you as zeale did <hi>David?</hi> ha's't not <hi>eaten you up?</hi> 'twill firſt, or laſt ſerve you ſo, yee favourites of Heaven. Chriſt's effectuall love is not laid out in vaine: for <hi>loving to the end,</hi> hee holds his object cloſe to himſelf, till he hath it where it cannot get from him: even in his owne man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and dwelling place. Chriſt drawes with <hi>bands of love, Hoſea</hi> 11.3. Chriſtians, if words will not faſten you to your Saviour, deeds muſt, he hath bands for you: and if hee get you in bands, he'l hold you faſt.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, it's coercive, both
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100079:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>within himſelfe, and alſo in all his members. What made him to veile his glory, become fleſh, and ſave his people, but love<note n="e" place="margin">Nihil enim eſt quod non toleret, qui perfectè dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git.</note>? <hi>he loved me,</hi> and what followes? <hi>he gave himſelfe for me:</hi> when once you have his love, you have his heart, whatſoever he is and hath: heare the Father ſpeake to deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſoules.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>God ſo loved the world, that hee gave his onely begotten Son, that whoſoever</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Quod omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus promitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſingulis promittitur.</note> 
                  <hi>beleeveth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi> So lov'd, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo infinitely, ſo tranſcendently, ſo incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſibly, there's a <hi>ſic</hi> without a <hi>ſicut,</hi> marke that wiſely and well.</p>
               <p>Doth thy unſutableneſſe to Chriſt, and unworthineſſe of Chriſt afflict thee? Remember his love will cauſe him to ſtoope to thee, and make thee worthy in himſelfe. And that very appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, if cordiall and reall, if hearty and ſincere: even that I ſay is a fruit of Chriſt's love, ſhed abroad in thy heart already, this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100079:30"/>abaſing of thy ſelfe is a lifting up of Chriſt in thine own ſoule, who hath already made thy heart his home. What force is that which moved him, who of himſelfe is ſo violent in all victory, to be ſo van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed with all violence<note n="g" place="margin">Quae eſt iſta quaeſo vis, tam violentia ad victoriam, tam victam ad violentiam? <hi>Bern.</hi> ſuper <hi>Cant.</hi> ſer. 64. Nulla vis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor pietate verá eſt. Triumphat de Deo amor. Id. Ibid.</note>? <hi>Amor eſt,</hi> nothing but the force of love: <hi>Nazianzen</hi> calls love a ſweet ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant<note n="h" place="margin">Dulcis, tyrannus. <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> orat. 28. in Maxim.</note>.</p>
               <p>In his members, what gives life and motion to all the parts of his body myſticall but love? all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theirs are the product of his affection to them: the more Chriſt's love ha's its perfect worke on a beleeving ſoule, the more lively and lovely are the reachings out of that ſoule to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Chriſt: the bleſſed light of the Lords favourable countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſhining out unto a Spirituall ſoule, makes labours many, after <hi>Meſsiah's</hi> preſence, love's coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive.</p>
               <p>Eightly, 'tis immutable, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not change, varie, or alter, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100079:30"/>length of time, diſtance of place, nor ſtrength of deformity, can worke an alteration in his love. The love of man is very va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable, we love by fits, and ſo doth every foole, he loves in his mood, while the pang laſteth: But as the torrent is up and downe, ſo it is with many lovers, they are either as high as the skies, or elſe as low as hell: either thoſe they love are the beſt with them, or the worſt living, becauſe they are unſteady, conſtant in nothing, but in incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy. But the love of Chriſt is alwayes the ſame, the injuries we doe to Chriſt, although they have their fruit in diſcomfort, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion the hiding of his face, with the ſuſpenſion of the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his love for a ſeaſon, which indeed is a hell on earth to a ſanctified ſoule<note n="i" place="margin">Subſtractio gratlae eſt maxima poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na. Alſt. in ſent: l. 2. tract. 30. q. 2.</note>. Yet theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, even theſe I ſay, doe not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or leſſen his love to his<note n="k" place="margin">Nube ſolet pulſa candidus eſſe dies. <hi>Ovid.</hi> Afflictio dat intellectum, quos Deus diligit caſtigat. Deus optimum quem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aut mala valetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, aut luctu afficit. <hi>Seneca.</hi> Unde datum eſt vulnus, contigit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſalus.</note>: for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100079:31"/>God can <hi>viſit tranſgreſsions with arod, and iniquities with ſtripes; nevertheleſſe his loving-kindneſſe ſhall continue with his,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Nocumenta, Documenta. Schola cruis, Schola lucis. Detrimenta corpotum, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crementa vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum. <hi>Greg. Iam.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and hee will not ſuffer his faithfulneſſe to faile towards them,</hi> Pſal. 99.32, 23. Chriſt can ſcourge his friends for and from their ſinnes, as well as for the exerciſe of their graces: and yet love them dearly, conſtantly, and ardently. <hi>In him is no variableneſſe, nor ſhadow of turning.</hi> Not ſo much as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, colour of alteration, or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>he will in no wiſe caſt you out, Joh.</hi> 6.37. and he that eſcapes the Lords affliction, may ſuſpect his owne adoption<note n="1" place="margin">Qui excipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turd munero flagellatorum, excipitur à numero filio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note>. Trees are rooted the more firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by ſhaking<note n="m" place="margin">Deus uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum habet fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium ſine pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato, nullum ſine flagello.</note>. The <hi>Perſian</hi> Kings ſhunned familiarity with their Subjects, and were ſeldome ſeene, that they might be the more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured<note n="n" place="margin">Perſona Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis ſub ſpecie Majeſtatis occulitur. <hi>Iuſt. l.</hi> 1.</note>: ſo Chriſt ſerv's Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</p>
               <p n="1">1. 'Tis not length of time that can worke, or occaſion an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in his love. <hi>It's everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100079:31"/>I have loved thee with an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting love,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19.</note> Jer. 31.3. <hi>Behold I will betroth thee unto me for ever.</hi> Wee may through tract and length of time, forget and be forgotten. As <hi>Joſeph</hi> forgot his Brethren, and was forgotten of them. Length of time may either wholly weare out out affections, or elſe coole and leſſen their heat, and ſtrength, towards our familiars: But Chriſt's love tak's not cold, is not cooled towards his, 'tis alwayes firme, free, full, fervent, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Hee hath ſaid, I will ne'r leave thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> The words are emphaticall; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, there is a duplication of the ſubject of the Promiſe, <hi>I will not leave, I will not forſake,</hi> and a multiplication of Negatives<note n="o" place="margin">Eſt negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicatio, ut fit vehementior pollicitatio. Eſtius in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note>, there are five negatives in the promiſe, by which he intimates, he will not, yea he will not ſurely, he will not forſake his ſervants: he will never totally reject them, he will not utterly forſake them.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100079:32"/>
                  <hi>I will not leave you comfortleſſe,</hi> or as <hi>Orphanes,</hi> as children without parents<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Non deſcrit, etiamſi deſe rere videatur, non deſerit etiamſi deſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Nam non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſit Deus, quando re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſit.</note>.</p>
               <p>Secondly, no diſtance of place were it never ſo great, yea, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though 'twere as great, as that which is betwixt the loweſt earth, and higheſt heaven: yet cannot this part Chriſt and Chriſtians, or impare the ſtrength of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections towards them, worke the leaſt alteration in his love: yea even now, although his glorious Majeſty poſſeſſeth the heavens, yet his heart is where 'twas, 'tis towards his Saints on earth. You bleſſed babes and friends of Chriſt! your head in the heavens prayes for you, pleads for you, takes notice of you, and all your ſufferings: he's <hi>in Heaven enter'd before you,</hi> but 'tis to make way for you, <hi>fit a place for you,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your roomes till you come, aſſure your ſelves he cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get you, doe not you forget him.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, nor can ſtrength of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100079:32"/>deformity worke a change in his love, he can love <hi>Job</hi> on the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, with his filthy carcaſe, <hi>Jery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> in the d'ungeon with his rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ragges<note n="q" place="margin">Anima quae nunc pannoſo veſtitu &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vili habitu, tegi putatur: in regno Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, &amp; nobilis Regi aſtans reperitur. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil. l.</hi> de vera Virg.</note>, <hi>Lazarus</hi> whil'ſt beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with his running ſores: <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> in the Whale's belly, though his head's bound up with weeds. <hi>Abel</hi> tumbling in his own bloud, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> in the ſtocks, with contemptible chaines: as he is <hi>no reſpecter of perſons,</hi> ſo neither is hee a reſpecter of conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: hee ne'r withholds his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, from his people in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the degrees, or rather the immenſities of of Chriſt's unſearchable love.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>INfinitneſſe ha's no demenſities, by finite conſiderations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt's love is of an infinite nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There's a meaſure in every thing ſait's our Proverb: but Chriſt's
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100079:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>love out-vies the worlds Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb: 'tis without me aſure, ha's no meaſure in it. It's nothing above Geometrie, that's an Art that may teach to meaſure the earth; but the Heavens are not ſo farre from the Earth, as the degrees of Chriſt's love are above all Arts and parts of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can you meaſure him who ha's mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd the waters in the hollow of his hand,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 40.12.</note> 
                  <hi>and meeted out Heaven with a ſpan?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt's love's immenſe, knowing Chriſtians can tell you ſo, and that no mortall can deſcribe its mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, we'l illuſtrate its greatneſſe a little, as the earthlineſſe of the inſtrument will permit, and leave the reſt to be revealed in Heaven, to all heavenly minds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THe degrees of love as well as the truth, ſtrength, force, and ardencie thereof, are as the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in which it acts, which may be ſhadowed out thus.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Chriſt loves more then
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100079:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>friends, there may be a knitting of ſoules among friends, as in <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>David:</hi> but did you ever heare of a knitting of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.1. vide 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 1.26.</note> friends of Chriſt! Chriſt hath knit your natures to his, you are one nature as well as one fleſh, are you glad on't? can the two natures of two friends be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in one perſon? Chriſt hath don't, this is the myſtery of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect love. The Law commands, <hi>love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe,</hi> but extends no farther: but Chriſt hath done a great deale more, marke beleeving ſoule! Chriſt's love to thee, hath excell'd the love of friends. For Chriſt lov'd thee not onely as himſelfe, as his <hi>Father commanded:</hi> but alſo more then himſelfe, as his love con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd. Hath hee not given his owne life to ſave thine? was not his ſoule wearie to the death, to refreſh thine, under the powers of that death which is death in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed? 'tis the ſecond death I
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100079:34"/>meane, to which the firſt is but a ſhadow. <hi>Hee was as a ſheep led to the ſlaughter,</hi> to free his ſheep from ſuch ſhambles. I lay downe my life for my ſheep, that's the heavenly voice, doe you heare it you ſheep of Chriſt? <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.15. Can <hi>Paul</hi> crie up ſome that would, for his good, <hi>have pull'd out their right eyes,</hi> ſo well they lov'd him? oh ſanctified ſoules! you have greater cauſe to crie up Chriſt? for hee would and did draw out both his eyes, yea his precious ſoule to doe you good, both now and in <hi>your latter end alſo,</hi> ſo well be lov'd you, and he is the ſame hee was, you bleſſed babes of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Friends may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure die for friends, and that's the greateſt love that man can ſhew, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.13. but Chriſt's love is more, he died for foes<note n="r" place="margin">Non exiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes immo &amp; reſiſtentes. <hi>Ber.</hi> ſup. <hi>Cant.</hi> ſer. 20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8.</note>, Chriſt can bleed freely, to make a reſiſting rebell live ſweetly, the life of God. Chriſt will crowne
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100079:34"/>thoſe with glory, that had a heart to crowne him with thornes<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pudeat ſub ſpinato Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Membrum fieri delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. <hi>Bern.</hi> in feſto. omn. Sanct. ſer. 5.</note>, if they'l receive him, <hi>he's kind to the unthankfull,</hi> that's his goodneſſe, hee can bleſſe them that have curs'd him, love them that hate him, pray for them that perſecute him, oh fleſh and bloud! thou canſt not doe theſe things.</p>
               <p>This is the praiſe of Chriſt's love, if you ſay he died for his friends, we may anſwer as he did, for his friends indeed, as being heartily lov'd of Chriſt<note n="t" place="margin">Pro jam amicis non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quidem amantibus, ſed tamen tam amatis. <hi>Bern.</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> qui habitat.</note>: though like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind friends, they loved him not againe. Or as <hi>Aquinas,</hi> not his friends as loving him any thing, onely his friends as lov'd by him alone<note n="v" place="margin">Non amici quaſi aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes tantum amici ut ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. <hi>Thom. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin.</hi> in <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han.</hi> uti <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rad.</hi> to 4. l. 4. c. 15.</note>.</p>
               <p>And, which is more, Chriſt in ſuffering was no murmurer in the leaſt meaſure; <hi>he was led as a ſheep to the ſlauohter, and open'd not his mouth,</hi> cloſed his bleſſed lips and was ſilent; Oh Lamb of God! thou art exceeding good, when wee ſuffer for friends, there is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100079:35"/>ſome heart-riſings in us, ſome harſh and hard expreſſions fall from us: diſcontented words are utter'd by us, yea much more when wee ſuffer for our enemies. But Chriſt was free from this, did <hi>not charge his God with folly,</hi> what ever he brought on him.</p>
               <p>Some grudge to doe him ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, who never grudg'd to ſave them, would they once accept of his love. Sweet Chriſt's ill ſerv'd of ſome, who have been well ſerv'd of him, ſome thinke all too much they doe for Chriſt, who thought all too little that he could doe for them, would they come in; But they'l not come to him that they may have life, ſad ſoules! I'le ſigh for you, thus he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth his owne cure, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints not the Phyſitian with his griefe<note n="vv" place="margin">Ipſe ſibi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negat ceram, qui medico non publicat cauſam. <hi>Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 118</note>, hee dies deſervedly who refuſeth Chriſt bringing life eternally<note n="x" place="margin">Merito peritaegrotu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> qui medicum non vocat, ſed ultrò venien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entem reſpuit. <hi>Muſculus.</hi> Prima pars ſanitatis, eſt velle ſanati. <hi>Seneca.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:100079:35"/>Secondly, Chriſt loves more then a Father, he loves children of Light more then Parents can doe theirs. <hi>David</hi> may wiſh hee had dyed for his <hi>Abſolom;</hi> but the heart's deceitfull, and chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſive in its affections. That love may ſeeme ſtrong, which in great undertakings and workings may prove weake. Chriſt did not onely wiſh a death once, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his from dying twice; but did alſo embrace it: will you heare his comfortable ſayings, in two or three words? 'tis this, <hi>I lay downe my life, no man takes it from me,</hi> few words but full of worth. They came from his heart; had <hi>David</hi> died, he could but have kept one alive, and that not long: but Chriſt's dying hath kept mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions alive, who ſhall never die the ſecond death. Chriſtians! what ſay you to your heavenly Father? can you love as you are beloved? how can you forget his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? you cannot live, much leſſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100079:36"/>die without the comforts of his love, without him yee can doe nothing, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſeor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim à me,</hi> ſevered from me<note n="y" place="margin">Calv. Camer. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Chriſt loves more than a husband, where's the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band that will marry with a black, deform'd, and adulterous wife? and when he hath got her, ſo love her as to lay downe his life for her<note n="z" place="margin">Quis enim poteſt ſic du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, ut mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur pro ea quam vult ducere? Si enim mori pro ea quam vult ducere voluerit, non e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it qui du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. Securus autem ille pro ſponſa mortous eſt, quam reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturus. <hi>Aug.</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.</note>? Chriſt hath done it, and thou knoweſt it, beleeving ſoule! if thou know'ſt what thou wert, when Chriſt betroth'd thee to him. Chriſt matcheth like <hi>Moſes, Moſes</hi> his ſpouſe could not be more defective in nature and outward comelineſſe, than was Chriſt's Spouſe in grace, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comelineſſe: and yet thou Spouſe of Chriſt! conſider, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> could not doe that for his Spouſe which Chriſt hath done for thee, <hi>Moſes married a certaine Ethiopian,</hi> but could not meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphiſe or change her colour<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Moſes E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m duxit uxorem, ſed ejus non potuit mutare colorem. <hi>Bern</hi> dom. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſt. octa. Epiph ſer. 2.</note>,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100079:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhe was as black, when made his wife, as ever ſhe was before: But Chriſt makes of black white, findes foule, but makes faire<note n="b" place="margin">In ſola ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma pulchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo, &amp; turpitudo apparent, &amp; ideo is ſolus vir pulcher eſt, qui eſt virtute preditus. <hi>Alexan. poedog. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note>, that's his method. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. All the glory of the Kings Daughter is within, as the Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint read the words, 'tas ever been Chriſt's lot to light of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually uncomely Spouſes, ſweet Lord! thou marrieſt meerely for love, when Chriſt ſeekes a ſoule he ne're askes the queſtion, what is ſhe, or what hath ſhe, he'le have her if ſhe'l have him, ſo great's his love. 'Tis not dowry or fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he have it? all he aimes at is love for love<note n="c" place="margin">Quam quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris alium, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſponſus, neceſſitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, vel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexionem, praeter amari &amp; amare. <hi>Bern.</hi> in <hi>Cant.</hi> ſer. 31.</note>.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Chriſt loves man more than man loves himſelfe, all men ſeeme to love themſelves, but really they doe it not, thy ſoule's
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100079:37"/>thy ſelfe, and that's neglected, whence are all thoſe cares and paines about thy carcaſe? why lay'ſt thou ſo much out on duſt? Is the bodies worth like the ſoule's<note n="d" place="margin">Quid de te, tu ipſe tàm malè meiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſti, ut inter bona tua no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis aliquod eſſe malum niſi tcipſum, <hi>Aug. in ſerm. de temp.</hi>
                  </note>? was not he found a foole that <hi>heaped up goods for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares,</hi> and plac'd felicity in them, <hi>and in one night, loſt them ſoule and all?</hi> canſt thou ſay thou lov'ſt thy ſelfe, and yet workeſt not towards Heaven for thy ſoule, thy better part? what ſhall the body be ſed, warmely clad, ſweetly accommodated, and ſhall onely the ſoule be brought to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty? Is this ſelfe-love to let ſelf die for ever, for lack of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king too? wilt thou bury a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſoule in a dead body, who for many years hath given life to thy members, &amp; at the cloſe of dayes wilt thou lodge it in a hell of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note n="e" place="margin">Qui fecit te ſine te, non ſalvabit te ſine te. <hi>Aug.</hi> Quid miſerius miſero non miſerante ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum?</note>? oh noble ſoule! thou art a ſpirit whoſe nature's to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive and act upward: but thy priſon the body hath been thy ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100079:37"/>Bleſſed God! what a bad caſe is ſuch a ſoule in?</p>
               <p>Others ſeem to ſeek out for their ſoules, ſeeme to ſhew ſome love to themſelves, but doe no more then grope after true bliſſe. Some ſeeke to be, and doe well in their latter end: but 'tis but as the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> grop'd for <hi>Lots</hi> doore in the darke. Reach after it they doe, but 'tis onely ignorantly, as ſome worſhip they know not what, ſo ſome ſeeke they know not what: others ſeeke they know not where, <hi>vitam beatam quaerunt in regione mortis.</hi> They ſeeke Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Hell,<note place="margin">Is eſt homo calamitatis fabula, inſoe-Ncitatis tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</note> the <hi>living among the dead,</hi> a living Chriſt in wayes of death. Is this to love thy ſelfe? The Lord bee good to ſuch a ſoule.</p>
               <p>Chriſt loves thee more then thou loveſt thy ſelfe: for his care is more for thy ſoule then is thine owne. Thou canſt let ſlip away precious opportunities, of ſoule refreſhing rarities, and ne're ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100079:38"/>the emptineſſe of all ſeene things: but Chriſt watcheth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, ne'r ſlumbreth, ne'r ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, waites that hee may be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to thy graceleſſe ſelfe. Oh ſinner! what's the frame of thy heart when thou ponder'ſt theſe things? Did'ſt thou ever heare of ſuch a friend that could over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love thy ſelfe in thee, ſeeke things for thy owne peace like to Chriſt? Is not this love of the higheſt degree? do's not this ſpeake him an inlarging good, when thou art ſtraitning thine owne bowells againſt, and towards thy ſelfe, in the things of thine owne welfare.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Chriſt loves more then a ſoule. For, firſt a ſoule may leave her bodie in the duſt, but cannot raiſe't up againe: but Chriſt will raiſe his body though buried in bottomes of greateſt depth. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the ſoule quickens with a borrowed life, but Chriſt quickens with his own life. Chriſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100079:38"/>loves his owne bodie, more then the ſoule can love her owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Two things ſhew the ſoule's ſtrength of love to her owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Feare of death.</item>
                  <item>2. Loathneſſe to die.</item>
               </list>
               <p>For the firſt, men tremble to thinke of that ſeparation which is then made betwixt ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it's as he calls it, a terrible ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration<note n="f" place="margin">Horrendum divortium, <hi>Bern.</hi> ſup. <hi>Cant.</hi> ſer. 26.</note>, not onely of the dead from the living, but alſo of the dead from it ſelfe, a ſeparation of the dead body from its owne ſoule, which is it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Timore caſto autem timeat, homo ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem à Deo. <hi>Bern.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, loathneſſe to dye, the ſoule ſhrink's at the bodies diſſolution, and they each of them grieve to part with each other. Is there not in them, who ſhall live for ever, a loathneſſe to die? which loathneſſe, ariſing neither from a deſire of poſſeſſing preſent plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, nor from a feare of ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring future torments in hell fire, muſt needs ſpring from this root,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100079:39"/>the love that is betwixt ſoule and body. <hi>Hylarion,</hi> when he was about to die, ſpake to his ſoule thus, Goe out my ſoule, goe out, what feareſt thou? what doubteſt thou<note n="g" place="margin">Egredere, anima mea, Egredere: quid times? quid dubitas? <hi>Hierom.</hi> in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta <hi>Hillarion.</hi>
                  </note>? diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering that his ſoule was loath to leave her earthly home, loath to goe to her heavenly Father, the onely Father of Spirits, oh the love it ſelfe of none, but of ſuch an one who is love its ſelfe<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>D. Walſ. ſer.</hi> liſe &amp; death of Chriſt.</note> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.8. God is love.</p>
               <p>Chriſt's and Chriſtians union is greater then that of ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, thus. 1. The ſoule is truly and properly ſaid to be in the body, but the body cannot truly and properly be ſaid to be in the ſoule, for 'tis impoſſible<note n="h" place="margin">Ultra poſſe non eſt eſſe.</note>. But Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>in his,</hi> and they are ſaid to be in him. 2. There is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter union between the one, then is between the other<note n="i" place="margin">Caput &amp; corpus unus eſt Chriſtus. <hi>Auſt.</hi>
                  </note>, and therefore the greater love: for the more the unitie is, the more is the amity.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Chriſt loves man more then man loves God, though you
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100079:39"/>take in the beſt of men within the limits of this concluſion. <hi>Abraham</hi> may give a Sonne, an onely ſonne<note n="k" place="margin">Sint &amp; in hoc parenti triplicata ſupplicia, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, chariſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quem diligis <hi>Orig.</hi> in locum. Fulmen non minus terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> quam ſi jubetur cor ſibi cruere, immo ſecum univerſo mundo in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitare. <hi>Paraeus</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.</note>, a ſonne he lou'd to the Lord his God in love, through many ſtraits, and yet not be ſo much in love with God, as he's in love with him: a man may give his owne life, ſelfe, and ſoule to Jeſus Chriſt, and yet not love as he's belov'd. For firſt, love in this life is little, and can you think its acts are ſo great; Nothing acts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the compaſſe of its owne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities. Secondly, wee are the Lords debtors, our lives are his by right: but Chriſt is debtor to none, he paid many debts of many thouſands, but ow'd not a mite to any<note n="l" place="margin">Promittendo ſe fecit debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note>. 3. Chriſt's love to us is greater then ours to him, for 'tas a greater fruit, his love makes lovely: but ours addes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to his beauty, wee may get by him, but what gaines he by us? can we augment his glory? that were to help the Sunne to ſhine,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100079:40"/>whoſe glory needs no increaſe. Deare friends! tell mee what thoughts have you of Chriſt's love, and what worke doth it make on your ſpirits? can you at laſt admire the height, depth, length, and breadth, of ſuch a grace, in ſuch a perſon as Chriſt is? you ſee, friends of Chriſt! all theſe lovers have done worthily,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.29.</note> and yet as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith of the vertuous woman, many daughters have done vertuouſly, but thou excelleſt them all: ſo may I ſay of Chriſt and much more, many lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers have done worthily, but thou excelleſt them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Diſcoveries and manifeſtations of Chriſts love.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SOme things have a greater ſhew than ſubſtance; but the things of Chriſt are no ſuch things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some men have got an Art to ſeeme
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100079:40"/>what they are not, theſe doe like themſelves, not like Chriſt: for Chriſt cannot doe ſo:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He's as good as he ſeemes, but cannot ſeeme the halfe of that he is, in himſelfe, and unto his, while they live in this inferiour world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some want Bowells, or elſe ſhut up thoſe they have in time of others need; but Chriſt abounds with Bowells, and they are alwayes open, never ſhut againſt his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hence is that multiplication of that mercifull word,</hi> Hoſea 11.8. How ſhall I give thee up? how ſhall I deliver thee? how ſhall I make thee as Admah? how ſhall I ſet thee as Zeboim? <hi>and the Lord gives you the reaſon of this his arguing, within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe his</hi> heart <hi>was</hi> turned, <hi>his</hi> repentings <hi>were</hi> kindled, <hi>ſet on fire within his bleſſ'ed breſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt's love, and the diſcoverie on't, doe paſſe th'apprehenſion of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall weights; but unto you who
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100079:41"/>muſt put on immortality: bee it ſhadowed out thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>DIſcoveries of love are either verball, or actuall and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. Chriſt diſcovers his love to his by words, or workes, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or actions. By words, Chriſt lets his know hee loves them, ſpeaking good to them, and of them to his Father.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by words of nomination, by the ſweet Epithets hee gives them, as is uſuall among all lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, ſave that in this; Chriſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrips them all: when hee is ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball he is alwayes reall, ſo are not other lovers. Theſe ſweet words demonſtrate love,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.15. <hi>Mark.</hi> 3.35. <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.5. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Dent.</hi> 32.9. <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Love, Dove, undefiled,</hi> and thoſe other words elſewhere, <hi>my friend, my brother, my ſiſter, my Jewells, the apple of mine eye, my children, my faire ones, my portion, my Spouſe.</hi> Are not theſe expreſſions full of love? doe not theſe words of Chriſt ſpeake you beloved? We
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100079:41"/>take it mighty kindly when the great ones of this world ſpeake friendly to us, and we thinke it a favour, a friendſhip more worth then gold. How will ſome plot, contrive, and lay their heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for a few good words from an earthly Monarch, Prince, or Potentate? Let ſuch behold the King of Kings putting out himſelf freely in ſweeteſt termes. His Spouſe lov'd to heare him ſpeake, <hi>let me heare thy voyce,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>for it's ſweet, and thy countenance is comely.</hi> Saints feele ſweetneſſe in their Saviours words: he gives his beloved good names which are <hi>better then precious oyntments.</hi> Chriſt alſo knowes his by thoſe names, <hi>Thou haſt told me ſaith Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that thou knoweſt me by name.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Though thoſe hee hath elected may keep from him many yeares, and not come at him untill their through converſion: yet when they come to him hee can call them by their names: he can call
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100079:42"/>out <hi>Saul, Saul,</hi> goe to ſuch a place, thou art a choſen veſſell. Though afflictions both of body and mind may ſo change men as <hi>Job</hi> was changed, by his noyſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, poore eſtate, meane dwelling, which was on a dunghill. Or as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was changed with run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fores, ſo as that a man that had ſeen them before, would ſay, that is not <hi>Job,</hi> this is not <hi>Lazarus,</hi> yet God hath not forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, he knowes them, yea, he knowes them by name, he can ſay this is my friend <hi>Abraham,</hi> this is my ſervant <hi>Job,</hi> this is my ſon <hi>Adam,</hi> tho'other is my child <hi>David,</hi> a man after my owne heart: hee calls them toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther as you doe your children by name, <hi>Fetch myſonnes from far ſaith the Lord,</hi> he cannot forget his.</p>
               <p>What the Heathen Oratour ſpake flatteringly of <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> namely that hee was wont to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get nothing but wrongs and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries<note n="a" place="margin">Nihil obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſci ſolet, niſi injurias. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.12. <hi>chap.</hi> 10.17.</note>, is moſt true of God, and Chriſt. He forgets nothing but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100079:42"/>the ſinnes of his people, <hi>I will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, and remember their finnes no more.</hi> The Lord blots out their ſinnes, that they condemne them not, puts them away that they hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, caſts them behind his back, as though he regarded them not, caſts them into the Sea, that they drowne them not, covers them, that they appeare not in the Judgement: doth not impute them, as if they were not.</p>
               <p>A ſecond ſort of love diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring words that fall from Chriſt's ſweeteſt lips, are words of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. <hi>Comfort yee, comfort yee my people, ſaith your God: ſpeake you comfortably to Jeruſalem,</hi> I ſaiah 40.1.2. O yee rectified Chriſtians! conſider the fruit of Chriſt's words, what fruits words ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Chriſt have. 'Tis ſaid of <hi>Elizabeth, when ſhe heard the ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of</hi> Mary, with the tidings of a Jeſus: that <hi>the babe leapt in her belly,</hi> and <hi>ſhe was filled with the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> The good woman
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:100079:43"/>was tranſported above her ſelfe, that not onely the babe; but her ſelf alſo leaped for Joy:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 2.41. <hi>to</hi> 5.</note> and ſhe brake out into ſinging, of God's great goodneſſe to her.</p>
               <p>Conſider what ſoule-raviſhing comfort there is, in words ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Chriſt. Chriſt's words warme well, as farre as they goe. <hi>Did not our hearts burne within us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk</hi> 24.32.</note> 
                  <hi>when he talked with us,</hi> ſpake to us? were wee not inflam'd with love, raviſh'd with joy, yea, raviſh'd in ſpirit, eſpecially <hi>when he opened to us the Scriptures,</hi> thoſe precious ſountaines of living waters? when Chriſt ſpeakes to the heart with power, he ſpeakes from his heart in love: and ſuch kind of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing muſt needs be very taking, in, and upon the Spirits of Saints.</p>
               <p>Tell me ô yee ſervants of the moſt High! when you feed, where <hi>he feedes his flock, when you reſt with him at noone,</hi> in the ſcorching times of trouble, from within, and from without, (tell me I ſay,)
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100079:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>Is not this fruit ſweet to your taſte? did you ever taſte the like?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3.</note> what, have you not found your hearts raiſed, your Spirits quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, your doubts reſolved, your ſoules filled with his marrow and fatneſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.5.6.</note> and that inviſibly<note n="b" place="margin">Pulcherri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam inſulam videmus, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am cum non videmus. Lypſ. ep. ad <hi>Cambd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note>? <hi>my ſoule ſhall be ſatisfied, as with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and fatneſſe, and my mouth ſhall prayſe thee with joyfull lips: when I remember thee upon my bed, and meditate on thee in the night watches,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, as if hee ſhould ſay, I cannot once think on thee, and thy goodneſſe: but it fattens my ſoule, and ſtrengthens mee: as a man is ſtrengthned with marrow: much more <hi>in the multitude of my thoughts within me, doe thy comforts delight my ſoule,</hi> Pſal. 94.19. and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, the good man is ſo full of the comforts of his good God, after hee had ſpoken peace, and comfort to him; that his mouth is too narrow for his heart and obſervation: and breakes out
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100079:44"/>thus.<note place="margin">139. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>How precious are thy thoughts to me oh God? How great is the ſumme of them? If I ſhould count them they are more then the ſands, when I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake I am ſtill with thee. viz.</hi> I cannot be from thee, I cannot be without thee, thou art ſo good to me. Thou man of God admire his goodneſſe, deplore thine own vileneſſe.</p>
               <p>A third ſort of Chriſt's love diſcovering words, are words of Promiſe<note n="c" place="margin">Quaelibet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina promiſſio eſt dilectionis Dei erga nos teſtimonium. <hi>Calv.</hi> l. 3. <hi>Jnſt.</hi> c. 2. Policitis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, in praeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ditior.</note>, promiſſary words; he diſcovers his love by ſweereſt promiſes: made to them he loves, even as 'tis uſuall amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all lovers: Promiſes that doe aſſure<note n="d" place="margin">In Dei pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſis nulla falſitas eſt, quia infaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enais nulla eſt omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas. <hi>Fulgent.</hi>
                  </note> them of ſpirituall helps and ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Firſt, that he prayes to his Father for them. Secondly, that he prayes to his Father in them, he prayes to his, and their Father for them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that their graces faile not. Secondly, that their natures ſoile not. That their graces faile not. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Satan hath deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100079:44"/>to have you, that he might winnow you, and ſift you as wheat;</hi> he would have you in his ſive to ſift out your grace, and preſerve nothing but the chaffe of your ſinnes to witneſſe againſt you:<note place="margin">Si homo, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelus, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angelus ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid promiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, fortè quis dubitaverit: ſuprema verò eſſentia Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus dei teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis intus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibente, quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam dubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis locus? <hi>Chyrſ.</hi> apud par.</note> 
                  <hi>But I have prayed for thee, that thy faith faile not.</hi> I will put you in my ſive, and ſift out your chaffe; but preſerve your wheat: for a witneſſe againſt Satan and all his fellowes, the evill Angels, that kept not their ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (as you ſhall doe) but fell from it. And this is the promiſe I'le make unto mine, that I will purely purge away all their droſſe, and take away all their tinne, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 1.25. Doe you doubt that your faith may faint, waxe weake, pale, and wanne, that your affections may bee cooled, and leſſened, that your zeale of God &amp; his glory may be quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? what of this your ebb of grace? I will pray the Father for you, that your graces faile not, And you ſhall have your floud of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100079:45"/>grace, as well as ebb. But I am troubled with ſuch temptations as I have not heard of, I am ſometimes tempted to beleeve, Chriſt will not pray for me; nor will God heare for ſuch a wretch as I am: well ſaith Chriſt, <hi>he is a lyar and was ſo from the beginning. Reſiſt him</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Debuit jux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta vos dicere non quidem ſurgite &amp; ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, ſed ſurgite &amp; reſiſtite. Inquit. <hi>Hier.</hi> contra pela. l. 2.</note>, and ſo weake is his power that he hath, and ſo ſtrong is the power that thou haſt of me: that <hi>he will flee from thee</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Idem horta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ut pugne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, adjuvat ut vincamus, deficientes ſublevat, &amp; vincentes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronat.</note>.</p>
               <p>Chriſt perſwadeth and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſoule of two things to confirme and comfort it. Firſt, that he hath prayed for as bad, as that ſoule can be. 2. That hee alwayes prevailed for what hee prayed, for though 'tis ſaid, that <hi>God heares not ſinners,</hi> and that their prayers are in his eſteeme as <hi>abomination;</hi> yet he heares his ſonne, for he is no ſinner, never was. <hi>Father I thanke thee ſaith Chriſt</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Tam refert quis, quam, quid?</note>, <hi>that thou haſt heard mee, and I know that thou heareſt mee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes,</hi> Joh. 11.41.42. <hi>The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100079:45"/>loveth the Sonne, and ſheweth him whatſoever himſelfe doth.</hi> Joh. 5.20. and hee loves his Saints though they have ſinned, in his Sonne. The Apoſtle gives a ſtrong reaſon of this, for God hath <hi>choſen us in him before the foundation of the world, that wee ſhould be holy and without blame: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in love.</hi> So that you ſee, Chriſtians! for your comfort, when the Father did chooſe Chriſt: hee alſo choſe you in Chriſt. Hence, although you are full of blame, blame-worthy in your ſelves; yea although very unholy in your ſelves, reſpecting the ſtrictneſſe that ſhould be in you: yet ſaith the Apoſtle you are choſen in him for this end, that you might be and appeare blameleſſe in this Chriſt before the Father. All this is through love, in love.</p>
               <p>Now Chriſtians! looke about you, remember and conſider what a Jeſus you have, how good
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:100079:46"/>he is, how dearly and greatly hee loves you, what a friend he is to you with the Father, and then tell me, can you ſhew unkindneſſe to this Chriſt? can you deale diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courteouſly with him in ſinning againſt him? I tell thee ô man, I tell thee ô woman, whoſoever thou art,<note n="h" place="margin">Etſi multi Gehennam omnium ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum ſupce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum atque ultimum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; Ego ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſic ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, ſic aſſidue praedicabo, multo accer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius eſſe Chriſtum of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendere, quam in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henna malis vexari. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. Matth. Hom.</hi> 37.</note> that haſt come under the working power of the Lords goodnes, thou canſt not willingly prove unkind to this friend of friends. And if thou doeſt forget <hi>the rocke whence thou art hewne, and the breſts that gave thee ſuck,</hi> as ſome have done: will it not grieve thy heart, pierce thy ſoule, and wound thy Conſcience, if it hath any tenderneſſe in it, to heare thy ſweet Saviour replie to thee as <hi>Abſolom</hi> to <hi>Huſhai,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Is this thy kindneſſe to thy friend?</hi> as he will doe if thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe his love, will not ſuch a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt as this be <hi>quick and powerfull, ſharper then a two edged ſword</hi> to dagg and ſtab thy heart?
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:100079:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>Conſider thy ſelfe therefore, and be to Chriſt as thou wouldeſt hee ſhould be to thee.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt prayes that thy nature ſoyle not, be not ſoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by ſinne, the beſt of men have uncleane natures: but Chriſt prayes they may be cleanſed in love, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.15. <hi>I pray</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that thou wouldeſt keep them from the evill of the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 20.</note> that they may never be ſtained with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the defilements of the world, and <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>Father ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie them through thy truth, thy word is truth.</hi> Cleanſe, waſh, purge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their ſoiling ſinnes, even theirs, and <hi>all that beleeve through their word,</hi> v. 20. Chriſt prayes for all his. And the meaneſt chriſtian if he do's beleeve, ha's a ſhare in Chriſt's prayers for his Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. What though the Lord replies not to a poore Chriſtian when he cries out to him about his ſoule, as <hi>Moſes</hi> about <hi>Miri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> heale her now? what if hee
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:100079:47"/>doth not heale now, even now, when thou deſireſt healing, yet heale he will, he heares his ſonne, and thy ſelfe in him, and will heale when healing is beſt for thee. Some languiſh under ſinnes filth, guilt, and preſſure, with a Spirit of bondage, many yeares, cannot beleeve their ſinne is pardoned, their ſoules purged: and yet at the laſt they find Chriſt, who is the meanes of eſcape from the evill of ſinne, doth waſh it away by his bloud, ſo that they can ſenſiblie ſay as that Martyr at the ſtake who had long waited for the Lords Chriſt, he is come, he is come. <hi>Yet a little while, and he that ſhall come, will come and will not tarrie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Chriſt prayeth to the Father in you by his Spirit, (which is another ſpirituall help and ſufficiency) the Spirit it ſelfe makes interceſſion for you, that is, the Spirit of God within you.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.</note> Thus, firſt by giving matter of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:100079:47"/>prayer to them, all the prayers of the Saints that are made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, are the dictates of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God and Chriſt. The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit dictates and works a ſight and ſenſe of ſinne, of a mans owne wants, inward or outward empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and unworthineſſe; A ſight of Chriſt's fulneſſe, worth and freeneſſe, for the good of all his people; as alſo what he is of God to every beleeving ſoule, <hi>viz. wiſdome, Righteouſneſſe, Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Redemption.</hi> Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you reveales himſelfe and his Father to you, Chriſt is ſaid to pray in Chriſtians; for they have his matter, uſe his matter. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are ſonnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath ſent the Spirit of his Sonne into your hearts</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Remanet quaedam ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantiae ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuritas in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectu ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum quam (ut etiam dicitur. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.) Quid oremus ſicut o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter, neſcimus, propter varios enim retum eventus, &amp; qui nos ipſos non perfectè cognoſcimus, non poſſimus ad plenum ſcire quid nobis expediat, ideò neceſſe eſt ut à Deoditigamur &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegamur, qui omnia novit &amp; omnia poteſt, <hi>Aqu.</hi> ſum. 2<hi rend="sup">•.</hi> q 109. a. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>crying.</hi> Chriſtians! when you crie unto God, Chriſt by his Spirit is crying in you, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:100079:48"/>out, <hi>Abba, Abba,</hi> Father, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, can you then doubt of being heard, when Chriſt prayes in you whom <hi>the Father heares alwayes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt in them, poures forth their requeſts to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that by words ſutable to his Majeſty, and their neceſſity: this is called the help of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>by reaſon of mans infirmity;</hi> and this help is afforded, becauſe <hi>we know not what to pray for as we ought.</hi> 'Tis good to have a hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per when wee goe into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a great God, eſpecially when wee are helpleſſe: for did not the Spirit help, who elſe can give ſupplie in ſuch a caſe? Or what can be pleaſing to God, ſave that which comes from God? can any thing lead to God, aſcend unto him, beſides that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from him? ſurely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; onely he that <hi>ſearcheth the heart knoweth the mind of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, becauſe that makes interceſsion according to the will of God,</hi> Rom.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:100079:48"/>8.27. God and Chriſt puts words in his peoples mouthes, as is clear from <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.2. Turning to the Lord ſay theſe words, <hi>take away our iniquities,</hi> remove our ſinnes from us; <hi>receive us graciouſly:</hi> be favourable to us, <hi>ſo ſhall wee render to thee, the calves of our lips,</hi> that is, we will bee thankfull, ſo <hi>Luke,</hi> 11. from the firſt to the fift. When the <hi>Diſciples</hi> deſired Chriſt to teach them to pray, hee puts words into their mouthes, ſaying when yee goe to my God, and your God, ſpeake thus, call him Father, the very name prayes for us<note n="k" place="margin">Ipſum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rat pro no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is.</note>, pray him to ſanctifie his owne name, to let his <hi>Kingdome come,</hi> his Kingdome of grace into the hearts of the graceleſſe, to let his will be done upon you, in you, and by you: and for manner, ſo an <hi>earth as 'tis done in heaven, viz.</hi> willingly, chearefully, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, with much willingneſſe, without any the leaſt wearineſſe, aske for bread for the day, all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:100079:49"/>for the comfortable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the outward man, aske forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, for he is bleſſed to whom the Lord im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes not ſinne, though hee hath little of the things and neceſſaries of this life. Beg, you be not lead <hi>into temptation, viz.</hi> not ſuffer'd to be tempted, or elſe be kept from falling under the temptation,<note n="l" place="margin">Jubet orare, ne in tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem duean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>i. e.</hi> ne ab câ vincantur <hi>Aug.</hi> l. de Cor. &amp; grat. c. 6.</note> and from being overcome of it, and that you may bee delivered from all evill of ſinne, and ſuffering. <hi>Yee ſhall aske what yee will, and it ſhall be done unto you, if yee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in mee, and my words abide in you, Joh.</hi> 15.7. <hi>aske and ye ſhall have.</hi> Chriſt names not what ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to let us know that gift is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that can be named<note n="m" place="margin">Non dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quid da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur, quia donum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra omne no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note>. Secondly, or without words, for prayer is mentall as well as vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; and although a Spirit of ſon-ſhip is a Spirit of Prayer, and every ſon of God is a man of prayer: yet ſome ſweet ſoules, as deare to Chriſt as others, cannot
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:100079:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſometimes, by reaſon of ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, and diſtractions of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and mind; (I ſay they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not) utter their minds by words, at the Throne of grace.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.</note> Now Chriſt by his Spirit helps<note n="n" place="margin">Eſt meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phora ab one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a, quae utrin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> admotis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ſuble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantur, <hi>Beza.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſo Luk.</hi> 10.40. <hi>The Greek wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>'s a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compound, and there's great force in it.</hi>
                  </note> theſe, ſometimes even to ſigh out their wants and ſorrowes before him, and obtaine <hi rend="sup">o</hi> ſometimes to groane out their deſires unto him: ſometimes by weeping, ſhedding teares, which have a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret language and voyce in the eares of the Lord of reſts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.8. Thou haſt heard the voyce of my weeping, and Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath wept for ſome<note n="*" place="margin">Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſe legimus, rifiſſe nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam. <hi>Salvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> l. 6. Cum Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus hominis ſuſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus Dei a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirat. <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Matth.</hi> 6.</note>, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the heart's ſo full of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, ſo ſad, and heavie, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can bee ſaid or done: then, even then the Spirit helps, and all through love.</p>
               <p>Chriſt ha's promiſed his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved friends corporall ſuccours; every morſell a Saint receives: hee hath it in way of a promiſe. The Lord feedes others too, but
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:100079:50"/>'tis onely ſo as he doth the beaſts of the field; in an ordinary way of providence: wicked men may have much, and yet inherit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe they poſſeſe not God in their injoyments, injoy not him in conjunction, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nection with the Creatures. <hi>Take no thought ſaith Chriſt, what ye ſhall eate, or what yee ſhall drinke, or wherewithall yee ſhall be cloathed,</hi> It's enough for a Gentile, a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, a ſtranger to God and Chriſt to bee cuttingly carefull for theſe things: that hath ne'r a heavenly <hi>Father</hi> to provide for him <hi>Doth your heavenly Father feed the fowles of the Heavens? and ſhall hee not much more feed you?</hi> Doth he cloath the Lillies of the field, better than <hi>Solomon in all his glory, and cloath the graſſe of the field,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Wicked men are like the graſſe of the field with their <hi>gloria brevis,</hi> whoſe end's to be burn'd.</note> which remaines but for a time? and ſhall hee not cloath thee, who ſhalt live for ever, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide for ever? theſe are ſome of Chriſt's comfortable love diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering words.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:100079:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>And many other ſuch like there be, which for number are as the Starres of the Firmament that cannot be told.</p>
               <p>'Tis ſaid that one <hi>Crane</hi> a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Chriſtian, though of meane eſtate in outward things, being about to die, and it being deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his friends, what ſhould become of his children: hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered thus. God that provided for the Ravens, will alſo certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provide for the young <hi>Cranes,</hi> and according to the good mans faith ſo it was, that all his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were well provided for in this evill world.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9.</note> 
                  <hi>There is no want to them that feare him,</hi> that is, of what is good for them, and to miſſe an evill thing is no injurie to them. If the Lord of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth foreſee, that riches will be a ſnare to one or other his ſonnes of love, and therefore withholds them from them: what doth that child want? ſave ſomething, which if hee had,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:100079:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>'twould make him more wanting in better things. Some have much of the world, and this hath been the fruit of it, the cares of getting and keeping, together with the feares of looſing the things of this life, 'tas almoſt drunke up all that delight, Joy, and content, they ſhould and might have had, in a ſpirituall God, Chriſt, and ſpirituall things. <hi>If any man loves this world, the love of the Father is not in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some like the bird that is faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a ſtone, would be on the wing, on high towards Heaven: but when they attempt to aſcend, they are drawne back, and held downe with a ſtone in the heart, and another in the hand. God hath given ſome <hi>their hearts deſire,</hi> but hath <hi>ſent leaneneſſe into their ſoules:</hi> and what profit was there in that? had it no been better to have wanted thoſe things, which fat the carcaſſe and ſtarve the ſoule, which is the moſt precious
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:100079:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>Jewell we have in this world? It is one myſtery in Godlineſſe, to have nothing, and yet lack no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. A Chriſtian may have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and yet lack nothing.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 22.35.</note> 
                  <hi>When I ſent you without purſe, ſcrip, and ſhooes, lacked you any thing? and they ſaid nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Divine Providence makes up outward wants another way: The Martyr had noe food, and yet he lacked none: for as hee had no meat: ſo he had no ſtomack, and all the Apoſtles wants, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, were but an as it were ſo,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.10.</note> but as it were dying, and yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>as ſorrowfull, yet alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, as poore,</hi> yet rich, and <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king many rich, as having nothing, and yet poſſeſsing all things.</hi> Chriſt was their all, as it were what it was not, for when a Chriſtian poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth God; he injoyes all: and what wants hee? ſurely there is none who live in God and his Chriſt, but ſhall be kept alive in this world, and if they be not 'tis
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:100079:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>no great matter; for this is not their Countrie: they will never be well and at hearts eaſe, till they be at their heavenly home.</p>
               <p>Chriſt promiſeth health alſo, and protection to his in mercy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 7, 8. &amp; <hi>c.</hi> 4.22. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.18.</note> all the haires of your head are numbr'd<note n="p" place="margin">Si ſic cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuntur, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perflua tua, in quanta ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitate eſt, anima tua. <hi>Aug.</hi> Sed ſicut Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillus de ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite, ſic nec momentum p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ribit de tempore. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note>. If that ſickneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringement doe ſurprize thee, yet, is it any more but an exchange of mercies? God ſhuts out <hi>Moſes</hi> from an earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> which was an affliction to him, but then gives him a heavenly one for it<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſita eſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatio. <hi>Calvin.</hi>
                  </note>, one mercy for another: did we not ſometimes meet with changes, wee ſhould like <hi>Jeſhurom wax fat, and forget the Lord.</hi> Afflictions, ſickneſſes, and weakneſſes, with wants and exigencies, are as need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and as good for ſome as their ordinary food. Yea, if they were not good in themſelves, as there is an evill of puniſhment as well as ſinne: yet God makes them good to ſome, they were <hi>good</hi> to <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.1. They
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:100079:52"/>give us a true taſte of the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that is, in the tree of evill: for we in nothing doe more taſte, and ſenſibly perceive the ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne than in ſuffering. Hence that, Oh <hi>the wormwood and the gall! my ſoule hath them ſtill in remembrance: and is humbled with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, Lam.</hi> 3.19.20. Here was the taſte of ſinne in the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring<note n="r" place="margin">Civitatis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertio eſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotum caſus. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note>. It brings to mind our ſin, as in the caſe of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Butler. Secondly, it is a mercy in that it drives us to the God of mercie. And meanes of eſcape from ſinne and miſcrie. In their afflictions the'l ſeeke me early<note n="ſ" place="margin">Num tibi cum fauces urit ſitis, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea quaeris. pocula. <hi>Hor.</hi> ſer. l. 1. Sat. 2.</note>, ſaith the Lord. Many perſons are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly remiſſe in walking with God, and calling on God, can keep from him for dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſucceſſion of dayes one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, ſometimes moneths, and ſcarce ſpeake a word to God. <hi>Is this thy kindneſſe to thy friend?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doe we not take it ill, if wee meet a friend as wee walke the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:100079:53"/>ſtreets morning and evening, if our friend gives not the ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of a good morrow, or a good even? Doe we not ſay he is proud and ſtiffe, or careleſſe and regards not his neighbour? what ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe yee will God thinke then of ſome that ſerve him worſe? Is it not pride that makes thee paſſe by him, not give him a word, and but ſeldome a thought? Is it not pride that eſtrangeth thee from God? yea, it is, and it will eſtrange God from thee, <hi>he knowes the proud afarre off.</hi> Is not the whole fabrick of mans body made upright? ſet upward? when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures are made to looke downeward, and all to ſignifie that hee ſhould mind God, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and higheſt things<note n="t" place="margin">Os homini ſublimi dedit Coelumquè videre juſſit, &amp; erectos ad fidera tollere vultus. <hi>Ovid. Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor. l.</hi> 1. <hi>ſab</hi> 1.</note>. Ah Lord! What will the end of theſe things be? will not the end be bitter?</p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt's love is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall, and is diſcovered.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In his doing for them.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:100079:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>2. In his ſuffering for them.</item>
                  <item>3. In his ſuffering with them.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt, he ſerv's them, wonder therefore yee Celeſtiall ſoules! he that is Lord of all is a ſervant to all; who are of the election of grace: <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.28. <hi>The ſonne of man came not to be miniſtred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but to miniſter.</hi> Now what thinke you did ſubdue this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering King of Saints? make him ſerve? was it not love? great love, free love: <hi>he tooke on him the forme of a ſervant,</hi> not onely of a good ſervant to obey: but alſo of a bad ſervant to be beaten<note n="u" place="margin">Non ſolum ſervi ut ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſet, ſed qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi mali ſervi ut vapularet. <hi>Bern. ter. quart. Heb.</hi> poenos.</note>. He was as if he had been the worſt of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, buffeted, ſtripped, ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, chaſtized, and pierced, led to priſon to Judgement, and to death, and for your ſakes hee was beaten and abuſed.<note n="w" place="margin">Cibus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis mura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit ſe, inpabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum pecoris, homine mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tato in pecus. <hi>Ber. ſup. Cant.</hi> ſer.</note> Now Chriſtians! did he not love you? what diſcoveries of love doe you deſire more reall than theſe? The Lord make you ſuch to him, as he is to you.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:100079:54"/>Secondly, in making exchanges with them, even beſt things for worſt<note n="x" place="margin">In primis de ſuis melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra contulit, in ſecundis de noſtris inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ora ſuſcepit; <hi>Aug.</hi> de tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por. ſer. 9.</note>: living quickning grace, for dead and ſottiſh nature. Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for fleſh; Mercy for miſerie; Riches for poverty. Glory for ſhame; a Crowne for a Croſſe; Life for death. Chriſtians! can you tell when you are well? all Chriſt, and all Chriſt's things are yours. Are you pleaſed? If not, the Lord of hoſts is diſpleas'd: you have his help, you have his heart, he is eternally yours; this is love indeed.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in making his ſervices eaſie to them, and that hee do's. (Firſt,) by ſuting and fitting his imployments agreeable to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities of his ſervants, his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements are not grievous, the more grievous then is the breach of them<note n="y" place="margin">Quo levi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s mandatum, eò geaviù. pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum.</note>; men of this world doe put their ſervants on doing more then they are able, oppreſſing them; which thing muſt needs make their ſervice irkeſome, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:100079:54"/>very unpleaſant. But Chriſtians! here's your comfort, that Chriſt's work doth never over-match the ſtrength of the Operator. 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 10.13. <hi>The faithfull God</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul will not ſuffer you to be tempted above what you are able to beare,</hi> it is a worke of Chriſt, and his ſervice to endure temptation. Chriſt's ſervants! conſider your Maſters love, what if <hi>Satan</hi> aſſaults you, 'tis not you he encounters withall; but the power of Chriſt in you; and ſo you ſhall bee able to reaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault Satan. His <hi>grace is ſufficient</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9.</note> 
                  <hi>for thee</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Sufficit mihi gratia tua, cum defici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> virtus mea <hi>Bern.</hi> apud <hi>Cornel.</hi> à lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in locum.</note>, and which is more, the Lord Chriſt gives thee a medicine with the maladie, a cure with the diſeaſe. Oh ſpirituall ſoule! thy ſtraits and reliefes come hand in hand unto thee, a meanes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape with the temptation; this inſtance may ſuffice. Thou mayſt ſee by this, how ſweetly, God ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's croſſes with comforts.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by a continuation of intrinſecall ſupplies, while's they
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:100079:55"/>are ingaged by him that there be no impairing of the ſtrength of his ſervants. Services of men doe oft-times waſt and conſume the ſtrength of ſervants: ſome are even worne out by them, have done ſo much for their Maſters, as that they can doe nothing for themſelves. But in Chriſt's ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, the Saints are as able at the laſt, as firſt, for <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga</hi> is with them. <hi>Such as waite on the Lord ſhall renew their ſtrength.</hi> Such <hi>mount up with wings like Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, runne, and ſhall not be weary, walk, &amp; not faint.</hi> The ſervices of Chriſt are all ſtrengthning, not at all weakning.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by frequent forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances when they offend, hee ſhews love in that, other Maſters are prone to make the worſt of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very fault: But Chriſt doth not tax thus, diſcourage, diſhearten, and diſcomfort ſo, for every fault. You, righteous <hi>Enoch's!</hi> that walke with God, can ſpeake bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:100079:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>things of God than ſo; if your indeavours be at the higheſt, that you doe what you are able, he makes no words of the ſinnes of your ſervices to diſcourage you;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.22.</note> 
                  <hi>his compaſsions faile not</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Compaſſio impaſſibilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te perdurat. <hi>Bern.</hi> de grad. humil.</note>, his bowells ceaſe not yerning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.38. <hi>being full of compaſsion he forgave them their iniquity, and deſtroy'd: them not, many a time turned he his anger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and did not ſtirre up all his wrath: many a time,</hi> often Chriſt is frequent in forbearances, he can ſuffer much, and ſuffer long. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians! is he to you a patterne of like piety?</p>
               <p>Fourthly, by exacting no more from them, than he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to worke in them. If God will have oneneſſe of heart, new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Spirit, contrition, faith, patience, love,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. <hi>c.</hi> 11.19, 20.</note> he worke it in you<note n="b" place="margin">Is dat qui mandat, qui jubet ille ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat.</note>. Friends! many complaine of want of power to ſerve Chriſt, they cannot doe this, or that, or the other: but is it not
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:100079:56"/>want of will? Chriſt ſupplies thy former want<note n="c" place="margin">Da domine quod jubes, &amp; jube quid vis. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note>; <hi>He will put his Spirit within you, and cauſe you to walke in his Statutes, and yee ſhall know his Judgements, and doe them; you ſhall be his people, and he will be your God;</hi> and if want of will be the burthen, he'l ſupply that want al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo. <hi>My people ſhall be willing in the day of my power</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Juvat idem qui jubet. <hi>Auſon.</hi>
                  </note>: power, and will goe hand in hand when Gods goodneſſe workes kindly in us.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, by a continuation of his preſence with them, for their aſſiſtance, when they faile in point of a right performance<note n="e" place="margin">Cum nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum agens, ſecundum a gat, niſi in vertute primi ſitquè caro ſpiritur per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuò rebillis uon poteſt homo licet jam gratiom conſecutus, per ſeipſum operare bonum, &amp; vitare peccatum abſquè novo aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilio Dei ipſum moventis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irigentis &amp; protegentes, quamvis alia habitualis gratia ad hoc ci neceſſaria non eſt via. <hi>Aqui.</hi> ſum. 1. q. 2<hi rend="sup">•.</hi> q. 103. d. g.</note>. 'Tis ſome eaſe to a ſervants mind, when his Maſter will put to his hand to ſet forward the worke: even ſo Chriſt do's ſpeed the performances of his people, by putting under his hand. Will not this incourage? what can be
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:100079:56"/>more inlivening to living Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? <hi>my ſoule followes hard after thee,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> hee was much in the thoughts of God, God was with him, and he with God: but what's the reaſon? <hi>thy right hand upholds mee. Pſal.</hi> 63.8. Chriſt's followers take hold on his Croſſe, and Chriſt will lay hands on't too, yea, and beare the heavier end for them. 'Tis with a Chriſtian, as with plants; which the heat, and influence of the Sunne makes to thrive; when Chriſt the Sunne of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhines upon them, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with them, they proſper: all things grow in their hands, and their comfort's in the hands of Chriſt; ſuch as is his preſence with them, ſuch is their life, and no other.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, by ſetting before them the ſame Joy, that his Father ſet before him in all his doings, and ſufferings; the beſt way to encourage a ſervant in his worke
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:100079:57"/>is to ſet the reward before his eye: thus God the Father ſerved his Chriſt<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2.</note>, <hi>conſider him therefore, leaſt you be weary</hi> of well doing, <hi>and faint in your mindes</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">verſ. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>. Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans! you are apt and prompt to wearineſſe in ſpirituall ſervices, to faintneſſe under the Croſſe of Chriſt; But ſaith the Lord,<note n="*" place="margin">ver. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>looke unto Jeſus,</hi> conſider his patience, his ſuffering, and remember, for your comfort, how hee now raignes, the greatneſſe and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt's pay, ſmoth's the the roughneſſe of heavens way.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in ſuffering for them<note n="f" place="margin">Multo effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catior Chriſti mors in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, quam peccata no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum: Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus potentior ad ſalvandam quam Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ad per, dendum. <hi>Bern.</hi>
                  </note>, true lovers will ſuffer to their loſſe; that they may gaine the thing they deſire: and having got that they love, their hearts are at reſt. Chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered loſſe even of his glory for a ſeaſon, that <hi>the travaile of his ſoule might proſper in his hands,</hi> and that he might inherit the ſonnes of his love, his peculiar portion. Chriſt ſuffered both in life and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:100079:57"/>death, and for their ſakes <hi>he lov'd not his life to the death.</hi> Conſider the greatnes of that work of dying for them, by the worthineſſe and fitneſſe of the perſon: which makes the ſalvation more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then elſe it could have beene; which appeares to have in it a heavenly glory, thus.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that onely Chriſt, and his death could be able to part that ſtrife which was betwixt an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded God, and offending man, <hi>he is our peace</hi> ſaith the Scripture, <hi>who hath made both one, and broken downe the middle wall of partition between us: he aboliſh'd the enmity in his fleſh; he made in himſelfe of twaine one new man</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.14, 15.</note>. Before this, God, and his people by election, were twaite, did diſagree, and <hi>can two walke together except they agree?</hi> if they could, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſhould a ſoule have, to walk and worke with an Enemie, truſt himſelfe in the hand of an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie? Now this bleſſed act of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:100079:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt's love, hath made God, and his people friends, hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>the wall of partition,</hi> ſo that now we may goe <hi>boldly and freely to the Throne of grace</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16.</note>, through Chriſt, who before durſt not ſee his face. Now that there was but one, and had not he undertooke it, there had been no other, 'twas greateſt love that he, in mans di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, would doe it. There are two reaſons of his fitneſſe in this particular reſpect.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he onely could diſcover, how great the breach was that ſinne had made.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he only could make the atonement, being in favour with God, the Lords equall.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that hee be able to beare the deſerts of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, onely Chriſt was able to beare the juſt demerits of ſinne, that wrath of a Divine Majeſty that was due to ſinne. Alas! hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity cannot ſtand under the wrath of ſuch Diety, a little diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:100079:58"/>of God you ſee, can breake us in pieces beat us to powder. Wee cannot tell how to behave our ſelves under ſmall afflictions, a little paine in the head, tooth, heart, bellie, back, or ſides, caſts us downe; when as all the paines and evills of this life, are leſſe then the leaſt of all our ſinnes; how much leſſe then could humanity ſtand under the wrath due to every ſinne of one perſon? nay, to every ſin of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon? It muſt be a God as well as a man that was able to doe this. This Chriſt did, hee ſtood under the ſinnes of all the elect, that ever did, or ever ſhall ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive in this inferiour world. Thinke of it then, <hi>was there ever any ſorrowes like</hi> to his <hi>ſorrowes</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.12.</note>? what a burthen bare hee? The Church uſeth the ſpeech to Chriſt, when ſhe was under but ſmall ſuffering; but might not Chriſt to dampe the Spirit of murmuring under a light Croſſe,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:100079:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>have ſaid ſo to her and all her chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren. You juſt ones! you ſee his fitneſſe to die for you.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that he be able to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for the offence, none elſe could ſatisfie Divine Juſtice, and a juſt Law for ſinne, ô! who then would ſinne, ſith ſuch ſuffering was required for ſatisfaction? Some men will feare to offend againſt the civill Law, if they perceive that any great ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on is required, any great mulct inflicted for the breach of the Law.</p>
               <p>Hence murthers, rapines, bugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are not ſo many as they would be, becauſe the Law exacts no leſſe then life in ſuch a caſe; and pray tell me, what's the life of man to the life of God? of Chriſt? it's nothing; yet ſome out of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall tenderneſſe, will weep for the death of a man; and that in great meaſure: but have not one teare for Chriſt, thinke not of him, are every day ſtriving as
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:100079:59"/>much as in them lies to <hi>crucifie the Lord of Glory afreſh, and put him to open ſhame</hi> by their ſinnes. If it be not ſo, what meaneth the breaking out of your piercing ſinnes, flinty hearts? ô <hi>fooliſh and unkind! will yee thus requite the Lord, and the love of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, that hee be without ſinne, he that is a ſinner can but die for his owne ſinne; as in the caſe of two malefactors, the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of the one cannot acquit the other, becauſe they are both under one and the ſame condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: Chriſt was thus affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for your ſakes. <hi>Silver and gold</hi> was not the price of our ſoules, <hi>corruptible thing's</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valid to this purpoſe; 'twas <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.</note>, not of a ſinner, but of one that ſaves from ſinne: a <hi>Lamh of God without blemiſh,</hi> ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe<note n="*" place="margin">ver. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, that he perſonate the party offending, ſo as that the ſame perfection of nature may
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:100079:60"/>fall for ſinne; which fell in, and by ſinne. Chriſt was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon perſon, perſonating, as a ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> and all his poſterity: offering the ſame nature for ſinne, which fell by ſinne, from the patterne of perfection, God himſelfe. <hi>By man came death, and by man came the reſurrection from the dead</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21</note>, man for man, perſon for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nature for nature, name for name<note n="*" place="margin">ver. <hi>45.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, that the ſatisfaction be eqivolent to the indemnitie ſuffered and ſuſtain'd.</p>
               <p>God ſuffered by the loſſe of his Image in man, ſo as that nothing, except the like in value to what was loſt, is of equall value in the Lords eſteeme. Thus did Chriſt and much more for the Elect, he gave to his Father a more refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and better accompliſhed nature then <hi>Adam</hi> loſt: for, <hi>Adam</hi> was left mutable, and ſo he might either ſtand or fall: But Chriſt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:100079:60"/>hath ſo ordered the matter for Chriſtians, as that, that part of the Divine nature which they have is uncapable of any ſuch mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note n="g" place="margin">Qui opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ut acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur ne diſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus <hi>Aug.</hi> de bon. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſev. c. 7. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6.</note>, ſooner may the Heavens bow downe to the earth, and the earth it ſelfe aſcend to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, darkneſſe it ſelfe be made as the Light: then that grace can ceaſe to be grace, till it becomes glory.</p>
               <p>Satisfaction muſt be plenary. Firſt, to put a glory upon Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the Juſtice of him who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acts the reparation, and that for the ſetting forth
<list>
                     <item>1. The auſterity of Juſtice.</item>
                     <item>2. The impartiality of it.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, thus it pleaſed the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bruiſe Chriſt for ſinners, to ſet forth the auſterity of his Juſtice in this particular, whereas he would not be content with a ſlight ſatisfaction or payment. God will have one worthy for another, yea, a perſon ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more worthy to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:100079:61"/>for the wrong, than was he that did the wrong: for, <hi>the firſt man was of the earth, earthie,</hi> who did the wrong; <hi>the ſecond man was the Lord from Heaven</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47.</note>, who made the ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the impartiality of Juſtice, in diſcovering, that the moſt high will not connive at ſinne, no not in his owne, and onely begotten Sonne, the Sonne of his deareſt love: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>he ſpared not his owne Sonne, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him up for us all;</hi> ſo that if the deareſt Sonne of his deareſt love will take upon him the ſins of the elect, he muſt beare their chaſtizement. <hi>Hee was wounded for their tranſgreſsions, and bruiſed for their iniquities, the chaſtizement of their peace was laid on him, and by his ſtriyes they are healed</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5.</note>.</p>
               <p>Could not Chriſt eſcape for ſinne that he tooke upon him? did not God ſpare a Sonne of love? where then, you ſonnes of wrath! can you bee ſafe from the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:100079:61"/>hand of Juſtice? Every man by nature is a <hi>ſonne of wrath, Eph.</hi> 2.3. and without this grace Chriſt had not been a Sonne of love, oh yee ſinners in <hi>Syon!</hi> ſtand amazed at this ſtrictneſſe of God againſt ſinne: and turne not your eyes from the things of your peace; leſt you diſcover your ſelves to bee loſt, to whom the <hi>glorious Light of the glorious Goſpell is hid,</hi> to whom <hi>the way of peace is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne:</hi> for God will put reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent glory upon his Juſtice, in the fall of ſome, as well as riſe of others, the damnation of ſome, as well as ſalvation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, doth not his wiſdome and Mercy deſerve to be ſharers in the glory too? doubtleſſe his wiſdome was infinitely ſeene in this<note n="h" place="margin">Sapientiae Dei quaſi per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix fovet filios, quos non pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit: quaſi gallina con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregat pullas ſub alis: quafi Aqulla pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocat ad vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landum. <hi>Bern.</hi> ſent.</note>: for who but the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and what but the wiſdome of a God could find out ſuch a way to ſatisfie his Juſtice, and propagate his mercy? that auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:100079:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>and lenity ſhould dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame breſt. That's a mirrour of Miracles, and are not <hi>his mercies above all his workes?</hi> who dare deny it? Mercy and Judgements doe proceed from God, as honie and the ſting come from the Bee; Honie comes from the Bee naturally, is not forced, but comes ſweetly and freely. But the ſting comes forth by provocation, ſtimulation. So Mercy comes from God ſweetly, and freely<note n="i" place="margin">Magna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Deo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, qui diffidet de ejus miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recordia. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> without forcing, for, who can extort from him? force him<note n="k" place="margin">Bonitas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victi non vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur, infiniti miſerecordia non finitur. <hi>Fulgent.</hi>
                  </note>? 'tis as naturall for God to doe good, as to be good, it's as impoſſible for him to ceaſe to doe, as to ceaſe to be. Mercy is his delight. Now acts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice are more ſtrange acts to him<note n="l" place="margin">Tua quidem malitia men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuram habet, Dei autem miſerecordia menſuram non haber; tua malitia circumſcripta eſt, &amp;c. <hi>Chyeſ.</hi> hom. 3. de poenitent.</note>, and they are called his <hi>ſtrange Acts</hi> in the Scriptures. Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:100079:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>comes not from him, till he be provok'd, and incenced by us againſt our perſons.</p>
               <p>And there is this reaſon of Gods proceeding in this kind, the motive or moving cauſe to his mercy is in himſelfe: but the motive or moving cauſe to acts of Juſtice, is without himſelfe, within us<note n="m" place="margin">Deus &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter miſerieor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diarum, ſed quòd judicat &amp; condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, nos eum quodammodo cogim us <hi>Bern.</hi> de nat. <hi>Dom:</hi>
                  </note>. So that when the proper cauſe (which is ſin in us) is removed, then that reall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of ſinne, that fruit and effect of ſinne (which is an incurring of the Lords diſpleaſure) is no more exiſtent. Hence thoſe ſayings of the Lord to <hi>Aſa, The Lord is with you while yee are with him: but if you forſake him, hee forſakes you.</hi> When wee keep up ſociety with God and Chriſt, he cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, nor can he ever forſake us, untill he be forſaken of us<note n="n" place="margin">Deus nifi deſerentem ſe non deſerit non nos deſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit fons, ſi nos fontem non deſeramus. <hi>Aug.</hi> in <hi>Johan.</hi> 32. Tu me non deſeris niſi prius ego te deſeram. <hi>Aug.</hi> in ſolilo. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note>, you ſee the cauſe and the effect. Then <hi>who is a God like to our God? that forgives iniquitie, tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſinne, and is not angrie for
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:100079:63"/>ever, becauſe he delights in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> You have ſeen, you children of Light! the fitneſſe, worthineſſe, and ſufficiency of your Saviours perſon, parts, and courage to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for you; and how truly hee hath made o're what he hath been, and don, even to you, for your good. Doth not this ſpeake you beloved? doe you not ſee God in the face, and acts of Chriſt ſmiling upon you? Conſider, was he thus fit to ſuffer for you? and is hee now fit to reigne for you? Then account him moſt fit to reigne in you, and to be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by you. But we'l glimpſe out the glory of this great worke a little more.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that higheſt Majeſty ſhould bow it ſelfe to loweſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity, we are but as wormes to him<note n="o" place="margin">Altus eſt Deus, humilis eſt Chriſtianus, ſi vult ut altus Deus, vicinetur illi, ille humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis fiat: magna myſteria, fratres, Deus ſuper omnia eſt. Erigis te, &amp; non illum tangis: humilias te, &amp; ipſe ad te deſcendit. <hi>Aug.</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.</note>. What? that the glorious
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:100079:63"/>God ſhould ſeeke for a Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with unglorious man, fallen man, man that had loſt all his comelineſſe, man that is borne like a bruit? that he who had for his aſſociates, a glorified God, &amp; glorified Angels; ſhould veile his glory, come downe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, become fleſh, and be like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, yea, the meaneſt of them, even a ſervant? Is not this glorious? all glorious? is not this love expreſſed? drawne out <hi>ad vivum,</hi> to the life?</p>
               <p>Secondly, the cohabitation of two natures in one, and the ſame perſon with harmony. Is it not the property of contrarieties to diſagree, not to exiſt peaceably in one, and the ſame ſubject? Fire ye know reſiſts water, (when injected,) with a fiery hiſſing; yet Chriſt you ſee hath effected and accompliſh'd this naturall impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility. He made his Godhead, and manhood, to dwell together in one perſon with peace: and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:100079:64"/>ſtrong was the union. Herein, even in this ſenſe, was that fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in him, which was typed out concerning him by the pillar of God, the cloudy pillar; there was Light and darkneſſe, two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries in one pillar. Were not our natures darkenes it ſelf, till he joyned his Light with them in one perſon?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in that mans riſing by Chriſt, and living the life of grace and glory, ſhould bee contrived both by Father and Sonne from all eternity even before man was, and had fallen by ſinne from his God. Chriſt's bloud was effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all before exiſtent<note n="p" place="margin">Sanguis Chriſti profu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, antequam fuit <hi>Bern.</hi>
                  </note>, that hee ſhould be, and not be, at one and the ſame time be in God, and yet not in the wombe or world, <hi>God hath choſen you in Chriſt</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>before the foundation, of</hi> the world, then certainly before you had being in <hi>the world.</hi> This Chriſt was for the good of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and thus Chriſtians were
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:100079:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>through the goodneſſe of God, and Chriſt. Chriſtians! you were in Gods favour before your generation, before you were begotten and conceiv'd, and God diſcovers it unto you, and that you are beloved, hee ſpeakes you beloved by Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. This may fitly be called a third part of the workes glimp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed glory<note n="q" place="margin">Qui in factis Dei rationem non videt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitatem ſuam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderans cur non videat, rationem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det. <hi>Greg.</hi> in <hi>Job.</hi> c. 9.</note>.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In that there is now ſuch a firme league of friendſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and his people, as if they had never been ad oddes in a way of enmitie.</p>
               <p>Chriſt and his people are good friends, now they ſpeake toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, conferre together, teed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, dwell together, lodge toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and live together<note n="r" place="margin">Omne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae cognatum eſt. Spond. in homilia. 2.</note>. Now ſaith Chriſt, my Father is pleaſed, all is well, and wee are well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed too. You are now no more a farre off, but are made nigh by my bloud, 'tis now I in you, and you in me, and both of us one
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:100079:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>with the Father, hee is my God, and your God, my Father and your Father. Is not here matter for a ſweet ſong? yee Singers of <hi>Iſrael!</hi> and ſonnes of God? can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not you make melodie in your hearts with the heroick acts of your Maſter? Should you not ſing praiſes for the Victorie of your King, the King of Saints, you could not ſhew your ſelves Royliſts of the Court of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, in that there ſhould be ſuch a ſutableneſſe, and uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the worke, unto the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and exigencies of Saints. Things may be good in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves, and yet, notwithſtanding, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found to ſute with the wants of the needie; they are not good unto them. As the body is not ſatisfied with things Spirituall, ſo the ſoule is not content with things Corporall. Externall things may ſatisfie the body, help it, relieve it in diſtreſſe: but when
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:100079:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſoule is in diſtreſſe, all the world is to it but like a great Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, it amounts to nothing. There muſt be a fitneſſe in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the eare is not pleaſed with light and colours, nor is the eye with ſoundes<note n="ſ" place="margin">Eis ſolum fruimur, in quibus volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas delectata quieſcit. <hi>Aquin. S. P.</hi> 1.2. q. 11. a. 3.</note>. The ſpirituall man is carried to ſpirituall things: as the naturall man to naturall things: and as in motion there is no reſt, till in a fit place; ſo in this caſe, you cannot quiet a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſoule with a thouſand worlds: Intereſt in God muſt doe her good, or nothing. Every thing is fitted for its object. What comfort doth a piece of fleſh yeild to a ſheep? and of what uſe is a rich paſture to a man? that onely is comfortable to us, that is good to us, and that onely is good to us, that agrees to us. The beſt diſh agrees not with him, who hath an antipathy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
               <p>Silver and Gold, Pearles, and things precious, yea, and many
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:100079:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>more ſeen things, as honour, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, and the like may bee good in themſelves, and for their uſefulneſſe, as they ſerve mens turnes. But applie ſeen things to an unſeen ſoule, and you'l find ſhe cannot reliſh them, ſhe feeles no ſavour in them, no more then in a drie chip, as our Proverb runs, and why? becauſe they doe not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to her as ſhee is a Spirituall ſubſtance, therefore not good to her. Now of all other good, God is the <hi>ſummum bonum</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Omne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo bono.</note>, and his workings towards his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are about the application of things neceſſarie for them, and ſutable to them.</p>
               <p>This great worke of Chriſt's dying for you hath ſuch a fruit as will fulfill all your deſires, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie all your wants, redreſſe all your grievances: for in all your comfortleſſe conditions, ye may fetch comfort from Chriſt's ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and death for you, you may fetch ſweetneſſe thence: as thus,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:100079:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>when you want, you may argue: did Chriſt die for a time that I may live for ever? and ſhall I thinke he will not keep me alive here<note n="u" place="margin">Dic nobis qui praeparas, quid praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras? replebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur bonis dc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſed qui bus? &amp;c. quaerimus qued oculus non videt, &amp;c. <hi>Bern.</hi> ſer. 11. in <hi>Cant.</hi> explicans il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud <hi>Iſayae,</hi> c. 64.4.</note> for a time alſo? did the Lord give Chriſt to me, and will he not with him give me a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency of other things, at leaſt, as much as is good for me? Thus little children, you may poſſeſſe your ſoules in peace <hi>that paſſeth underſtanding.</hi> Thus the Apoſtle did, <hi>my God ſhall ſupply all wants,</hi> yours and mine, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>He that ſpared not his owne Sonne, but delivered him up for us all, how ſhall hee not with him freely give us all things,</hi> even all that he hath?</p>
               <p>The diſtinction of goods in <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> is exceeding memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, remarkable, and ſweet; There is ſaith hee, <hi>Bona Throni,</hi> and there is <hi>bona ſcahelli,</hi> goods of the Throne of bliſſe and grace, as God, Chriſt, and whatſoever ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall good hee conferres. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, goods of the footſtoole,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:100079:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>as the Creatures and comforts of this life, the accommodations of this world, whence wee may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre. That God, and the godly: Chriſt, and Chriſtians: as they have but one Throne, which is heavenly, (and that to them all) ſo alſo they have but one foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole. Now God makes the earth his footſtoole, ſo ſhould the godly doe alſo<note n="vv" place="margin">Si terram amas, terra es: ſi Deum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, quid vis, ut dicam? Deus es. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note>. Chriſtians ought in a good ſenſe, to lay the world, and the things of the world, under the ſoles of their feet<note n="x" place="margin">Quam ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det mihi ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, cum Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum intueor? <hi>Adrian.</hi> Pedibus dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat, terram tangentibus. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Chryſt.</hi> hom. 2. de incomp. De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i. nat.</note>: and not make them and prize them as the Crowne of their head. And eſpecially when they hinder you from being crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Chriſt's Crowne, which is a Crowne of glory, and your greateſt dignitie.</p>
               <p>Now Chriſtians! conſider by this, and what hath been ſaid, what Chriſt, and this bleſſed act of Chriſt is to you: how that you have the goods of the Throne, and now God having given you
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:100079:67"/>Chriſt, having procured for you ableſſed Throne to ſet your ſelves upon, what cauſe have you to be troubled, if he denies you, or takes from you a footſtoole, whereon to ſet your feet? <hi>Let not your hearts be troubled, you beleeve in God; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve alſo in Chriſt,</hi> and be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for ever, yea, <hi>beleive his Prophets, and you ſhall proſper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond diſcoverie of love by ſuffering on the behalfe of his, is his ſuffering with them. <hi>In all their afflictions he was afflicted, and the Angel of his preſence ſav'd them. In his love, and his pitie hee redeemed them, and he hare them and carried them all the dayes of old.</hi> 'Tis ſome comfort to have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion in ſuffering<note n="y" place="margin">Comes in via, pro ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiculo eſt.</note>, 'tis much more comfortable to have a hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping companion, that will take off ſome of a mans burthen. <hi>Hee hath laid help on one that's mighty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, Chriſt is with his in loſſes, he beares a ſhare of thoſe loſſes, they ſhall not be all loſſe to them
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:100079:68"/>that feare him: he will give them ſomething againe, yea, ſome better thing, then what they have loſt for him, and in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or going along with him: and though the world bee but as loſſe to a ſoule; yet <hi>Godlineſſe is great gaine with contentment; He that loſeth his life for Chriſt, and the Goſpels ſake, ſhall ſave it,</hi> Mark. 8.35. <hi>Chriſt will make up and repair the loſſe againe, and do's not hee give</hi> a better thing than this life in the roome on't? What's this life, and all the accommodations thereof to that life which is above? the life of the world's ignoble, moſt mean, and paſſing poore to the life of God, and the glorified in Heaven. Then friends! what looſe you? can you tell? I tell you, that to die here, is to begin to live for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hereafter.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in Infringements and impriſonments of the body hee ſuffers with them, gives reſt unto them<note n="z" place="margin">Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Deus, tranquillat omnia, &amp; qai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum aſpice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, quieſcere eſt. <hi>Bern.</hi> in <hi>Cant.</hi> 23.</note>: &amp; is it not better you ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:100079:68"/>ſoules to be in priſon with Chriſt, than to bee at Liberty without him? nay, is it not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be in Hell with him, than in heaven without him? (if ſuch a thing could be?) doth not his preſence prove a Heaven<note n="a" place="margin">Chriſtus nobiſcum. 1. Politicè, ut Rex in Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no; Dux in exercitu. 2. Occonomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cè, ut Pater in domo. 3. Ethicè, ut ratio in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. 4. Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicè, ut anima in corpore, <hi>Cornel.</hi> à la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide</note>? what's the Heaven above, but the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God and Chriſt, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians! tell me: when you injoy much of Chriſt in the cloſet, or Congregation: when you feele the warmth, heat, and vigour of all his love and ſpirituall graces working upon your drooping Spirits, doe they not revive you? put much life in you? his <hi>words are Spirit and life,</hi> much more then are his works. Is it not your Heaven to enjoy, and for your ſoules to poſſeſſe their beloved's preſence<note n="b" place="margin">Heu Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Deus, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra hora, &amp; brevis mora. <hi>Bern.</hi> in <hi>Cant.</hi> ſer. 13. Res delicata eſt Spiritus Dei. <hi>Tertu!.</hi> Memor ſum, quanta pace fruebar, cum in Domino gaudebam, ideò nunc magis doleo, quia ſcio, quid perdidi, ſcio quàm maxima bona amiſi, redde quod per peccatum mihi abſtuli, red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de quod meâ culpâ perdidi. <hi>Savanarol.</hi> medit in <hi>Pſal.</hi> Miſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp;c.</note>?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in wounds, or hurts of the body or mind, if <hi>Saul</hi> goes
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:100079:69"/>to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and treads but on the feet of Chriſt, the meaneſt and loweſt of his ſervants. Doth not Chriſt bow his head, yea, all his body to ſave them? will it not make him crye out, <hi>Saul, Saul,</hi> why doeſt thou tread on my feet, <hi>perſecute me</hi> in the leaſt of my members? yea, certainly had he ne'r opened his mouth before, yet then as the dumbe ſonne of <hi>Craeſus,</hi> by ſtraining his voice had the ſtrings of his tongue unloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, when he ſaw his Father like to be butchered, crying, Oh! kill not King <hi>Craeſus:</hi> ſo Chriſt (could the former be which cannot be in him yet) then, when they ſuffer, he ſuffers with them, and cries as to <hi>Saul.</hi> Kill not my children, pierce me not, cut mee not in pieces, rob not, impriſon me not, he now plainely ſpeakes this in our eares by his word, could wee but mind it. Chriſtians! when you are touch'd with a hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full touch (ſo ſenſible is hee,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:100079:69"/>that) he is touch'd in the apple of his eye too, his eye ſmarts whoſe you are, and hee that made eyes, aſſure your ſelves, will ſoone heale that eye ſore, when 'tis ſeaſonable to doe it.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, in hurts of the mind. Are you wounded in Spirit, troubled in mind, tempted? he is tempted with you, wounded with you, troubled with you, is not this love, diſcover'd? Now hee is in Heaven, he is touch'd with a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, of your infirmities on earth<note n="c" place="margin">Inchoata in incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta in aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione, <hi>Cornel.</hi> à Lapide.</note>. Are you tempted? ſo was he, and that <hi>in all points like to you, ſinne being excepted, viz.</hi> ſinne did not tempt him as it doth you, but then he was tempted by Satan to ſinne, as well as Satan tempts you to ſinne<note n="d" place="margin">This I take to be the ſenſe of the place.</note>; inſtance that ſore temptation, to caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe downe from the pinacle of the Temple, to murther himſelf; and that temptation hee tempted him withall to commit Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, to fall downe and worſhip a
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:100079:70"/>Devill like a Heathen: hee alſo tempted him to diſtruſt, infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, when he would have had him make bread of ſtones, as though God could not live without bread, or as though there were not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of God in the bleſſed man, to ſuſtaine him a little longer, yea, for ever (if he pleaſed) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out food.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the ends of Chriſi's love.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EVery thing hath its end</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.18.</note>, <hi>and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing is ſuch as its end is, as the thing is towhich it tends: all's well that ends well, that's the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, not more ancient then true, 'tis the end that crowns the action; when God would prove a perſon, action, or thing to be good or evill, he takes this courſe, obſerves, (and bids us obſerve alſo) what the end of the perſon or thing is, at which it aimes or tends,</hi> marke
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:100079:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>the perfect man, and behold the upright man, <hi>ſaith the</hi> Lord, for the end of that man is<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.37.</note> peace, <hi>though hee ha's trouble in his beginning and progreſſe, yet ha's he peace in his end,</hi> viz. <hi>his way tends to peace, though hee ſowes in teares, yet hee reapes in joy, for Light, is ſowne for the Righteous, and gladneſſe for the upright in heart; men ſow to the end they may reape. Thus he proves an upright man to be a good man, by his good end. So ſaith he,</hi> the end of the wicked ſhall be cut off.</p>
               <p>Viz. <hi>He ſhall miſſe of all that hee aimes at, hee thinkes whatſoever his life be, his death ſhall be good, he aimes at happines after a ſort, but takes aſunder the meanes, from the end; when ſuch an one</hi> dies, all his thoughts periſh, <hi>where is his</hi> hope when God takes away his ſoule, <hi>ſaith</hi> Job, <hi>either his ſinne with himſelfe ſhall have no end, for ſinne in its fruits goe to hell
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:100079:71"/>with him, lives for ever with him, ſinnes are his workes and they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, or, ſecondly, his end ſhall be, and that moſt certainly, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his never ending tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by paine of loſſe and ſenſe, together,</hi> viz. <hi>his ſinne tends that way, leads thither. Some deſire Heaven but 'tis not ſo much for the ſocietie of God and Chriſt, as from a carnall conceit, that there's no want, there they ſhall have fulneſſe. Doe not carnall men dreame of carnall eating in Chriſt's Kingdome? happie (ſaid the Jewes) are they who ſhall eat bread with thee in thy Kingdome; but this end ſhew'd their deſire was carnall; for Chriſt reproves them, when he tells them, the Kingdome of Heaven conſiſts not in meats, or drinkes, but in Righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe. Every true lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver propounds to himſelfe his end, ha's his end, and that's true of Chriſt, hee hath ends for which he loves, and to which his love tends.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:100079:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>His ends are ſuch as theſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>To make his object lovely.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>To preſent his Spouſe blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>To keep the ſoule ſtainleſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>To ſave the ſoule harmeleſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>FIrſt he loves to make his love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his owne bleſſed ſight, and unto his owne glorious ſelfe. Chriſt loves comely Chriſtians, Chriſt's frame on a Chriſtians ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is a Chriſt-aluring beautie: a choice Spouſe's diſtance from her loyall husband is a cord of love to draw his preſence to her, long ſuſpenſion of perſonall fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip makes communion ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when injoy'd. Chriſt's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is good to Chriſtians, and communion with them is good to him, a ſoules diſtance from her husband Chriſt is verie great, yet many pledges of deareſt love paſſe betwixt them, ſomething of Chriſt, being in the ſoule, brings all Chriſt to dwell there; he loves
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:100079:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>himſelfe, and delights to dilate where himſelfe is. Some love to fulfill luſt and natures fancie; but Chriſt loves that his object may be lovely, to himſelfe, and all his off-ſpring. The bridegroome loves to ſee his Bride adorn'd on a bridall day, would have her as neat as hand can make her, that her aſpect may bee pleaſing to him, Chriſt loves to cloath his people with a heavenly glory, hee loves a ſoule, that he may preſent it to himſelfe a glorious Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 'tis inward Glory I now ſpeake of, Chriſt hath no luſt to feed, ſinnes not found in him he ſeekes nelther bodies pelfe, nor the minds riches, ſweet <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> thy ends are good.</p>
               <p>Chriſt ſets his love on naked ſoules; In ſome parts of the world, ſome buy their wives and cloath them, ſo doth Chriſt in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very corner of the earth gives himſelfe for them, and then puts a glory upon them.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:100079:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt's glory is transforming, ſome have ſeene it <hi>as in a glaſſe,</hi> and have been <hi>changed by it into the ſame Image, from glory to glory, even by the Spirit of the Lord</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</note>. Chriſt himſelfe aſſum'd our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; that he might cloath and adorne us with his: like to like, ſaith the Proverb, Chriſt loves his object to make it like him, and then cloſ'es with it, cannot ſtick looſe to it: ſo pure's his love. Other lovers may alter in their love, becauſe they cannot aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their objects luſtre, amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſpect; but Chriſt can make his object as comely as hee will; then where is the ground of change? not in the object, not in the Subject, therefore not at all. <hi>I the Lord change not,</hi> that's his ſaying, who is immutable.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt loves to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his object blameleſſe, both to himſelfe, and alſo before his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Some lovers will find no fault in the <hi>objects</hi> they liſt to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:100079:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>but having receiv'd them, find nothing elſe in them but faults: is this to love in truth? you earthlie ſenſuall lovers! Chriſt findes out faults before he eſpouſes a ſoule to himſelfe: but then through love covers them, buries them, forgets them: Chriſt never upbraids a ſoule with what he hath formerly been and done, <hi>God upbraids no man.</hi> Some ſpeak well of that they like, untill they have got it, and then the worſt word they have's too good for't: but Chriſt ſpeakes worſt of ſoules before hee's wedded to them, but when of <hi>twaine they are one fleſh,</hi> he ſpeaks and makes the beſt he can of them, and the leaſt good that's in them: hee cannot <hi>breake a bruiſed reed,</hi> nor can hee <hi>quench the ſmoaking flax:</hi> hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not rip up old breaches betwixt his Spouſe and him, but he's good at kindling ſmalleſt ſparkes of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace, though buried in a heap of aſhes: he is wont to make
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:100079:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>much weakneſſe little, and little ſtrength much. Some Lovers will hide nothing they know, by thoſe they have ſeem'd to love, will you call this love? 'tis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect hatred; but heavenly favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites! your heavenly husband's not ſo unkind, he covers all evills, and uncovers all good in them hee loves.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.12.</note> 'Tis ſaid he's <hi>able to preſent blameleſſe before his Father, with exceeding great joy</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Iude <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note>, and he's as active, as able in ſuch a kind of preſentation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he loves to preſent his object ſpotleſſe, Chriſt ſets his love on ſoules to cleanſe them<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27.</note>, and ſanctifie them to his owne, and his Fathers uſe.</p>
               <p>Satan loves to have ſoules that he may ſtaine them, pollute them, bereave them of their glorie, and Chriſt's Image that's in them, he's all for ſoiling of ſoules, that he may foile them, &amp; inſnare them; but Chriſt takes out the ſpots of his owne fleſh; he ſets his love
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:100079:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>on a ſoule to waſh it from all <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of fleſh and Spirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.6.7.</note> the ſoules time of miſerie, is Chriſt's time of mercy: <hi>when thou waſt in thy bloud, I ſaid to thee live, and thy time was the time of love. John</hi> tells the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia, Chriſt lov'd us, and then waſh'd away our ſinnes by his bloud,</hi> heavenly husband! thou lov'ſt to good purpoſe. Chriſt loves to make holy as well as happie, he would have her without blemiſh, ſpot, or wrinckle.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Chriſt love's that he may ſave harmeleſſe, preſerve his object free from danger; Satan loves to deſtroy, but Chriſt loves to ſave. All Chriſt's favours run into this: the ſoules ſalvation of whom he loves: he's cal'd the <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of his body the Church;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23.</note> the head you know contrives and adviſe's for the whole body. Such a head is Chriſt, he came to <hi>ſave,</hi> as well as <hi>ſeeke loſt ſoules.</hi> When Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are in Chriſt, their ſelves and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:100079:74"/>ſoules are in ſafe hands,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 10.29.</note> 
                  <hi>no man ſhall pluck them out of my Fathers hand</hi> ſaith Chriſt, &amp; what power's like to his: Spouſe of Chriſt! thou mayſt truſt thy ſelfe with thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Husband, put thy life in his hand; for hee <hi>came not to deſtroy</hi> the beleeving <hi>world, but to ſave it.</hi> Oh you ſonnes of <hi>Sion!</hi> how carefull is Chriſt of you? <hi>his eye is upon you, his eare open to your cry;</hi> Chriſt watcheth his children as you watch yours, he'l not let a child goe out of his ſight, leaſt he catch a fall, and bruiſe or maime himſelfe, and ſpoile his beauty, and when he do's get a fall, Chriſt's eares are open, hee can quickly heare him crie, and then he gives him a helping hand, till he's riſen againe. You are in his hand, and in his heart, and ſhall hereafter dwell in his heavens, what would you more? And now my friends! that Chriſt hath ſhew d his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by doing and ſuffering for you, he expects action from you
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:100079:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>towards him, and for him.</p>
               <p>Conſider, intelligent hearts!</p>
               <p>Firſt, is not he active for you? he praies for you, pleads for you at the Throne of grace, againſt the accuſer of the brethren: then drink not in forſaken ſins, againſt which both your ſelves, and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our alſo, hath put up prayers with <hi>teares, and ſtrong cries in the dayes of his fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly: are not Satans vaſſalls active for their Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Doe they not lay their heads and hearts together? unite all their forces, to follow that Prince, who rules in the aire, and workes in the children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to advance his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, inlarge his Dominion, as Hell hath inlarg'd her ſelfe? doe not they ſeeke to make his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelites many? and ſhall the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of darkneſſe be wiſer, and more active in their generation, and for their Prince? then are the children of Light in their
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:100079:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>generation &amp; for their King and Saviour<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.20.</note> Jeſus Chriſt? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid. <hi>Tell it not in</hi> Gath, <hi>publiſh it not in the ſtreets of</hi> Askelon, <hi>leaſt the daughters of the Philiſtims rejoyce, and leaſt the daughters of the uncircumciſed triumph.</hi> Love de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves love; oh, you children of Light! you cannot give warmth to your garments, but you ſhall receive't againe. Oh then! bee rooted and grounded in faith with love. <hi>Comprehend you with all the Saints, what the height, length, depth, &amp; breadth,</hi> of <hi>Chriſt's love is.</hi> Then ſhall you ſing Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah to God in the higheſt Heavens, when the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment ſhall bee in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lambe, with excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great Joy to Juſt ones<note n="e" place="margin">Secundum laborem acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pient, non ſecundum proventum, <hi>Bern.</hi> Non meritis operantis ſed miſeratione donantis. <hi>Aug.</hi> Deus coronat dona ſua, non merita noſtra.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
